Music
Music
No copyright repentance
No copyright repentance
Applause
Applause
I have seen some colleagues in the hospital
我有看到一些院內的同仁
and some of our
還有一些我們的
former old chief
以前的舊長官
And some senior colleagues
還有一些資深同仁
Thank you very much for coming
非常謝謝大家來參加
Our Information Feast Today
我們今天的資訊饗宴
our today
我們今天的
Everyone has information
大家手上都有資料
Our speech today is given by
我們今天的演講是由
You Xiaohua Associate Researcher
游孝華副研究員
Research Associate at the Institute of Chemistry
在化學所的副研究員
tell us
給我們來講
organic bioelectronics
有機生物電子
Mainly to talk about electronic components
主要是要談電子元件
Combination with biomedicine
和生物醫學的結合
So here I am very briefly
所以我在這裡非常簡短的
let me introduce
跟大家介紹一下
Our keynote speaker today is Dr. You Xiaohua
我們今天的主講人游孝華博士
he is from
他是從
Graduated from Department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University
台灣大學化學系畢業
Then to the United States to give birth
然後到美國生肇
MIT
在美國麻生理工學院
Received a doctorate in planning
拿到了有計畫學的博士學位
did some
做過一些
After postdoctoral research
博士後研究以後
arrived in singapore
到了新加坡
senior researcher
擔任資深研究員
Then to Japan
然後又到了日本
their physical and chemical
他們的理化
RIKEN's so-called RECOM
理化學研究所所謂的RECOM
Serve as an independent backbone researcher
擔任獨立主幹研究員
in 2013
在2013年
about 4 years ago
大概不到4年前
just came back
才剛剛回到
Institute of Chemistry, Academia Sinica
我們中央研究院化學所
Now working as an associate researcher
現在擔任副研究員
so very happy for him
所以很非常高興他
outside
在外面
coin
生造
after various experiences
各種經驗之後
Return to Academia Sinica to serve
回到台灣中央研究院來服務
PhD research expertise
博士的研究專長
is organic materials chemistry
是有機材料化學
high polymer chemistry
高分子化學
Nanobiotechnology
奈米生物科技
biomaterial interface, etc.
生物材料介面等等
The common denominator here is
這裡頭的共同點就是
this is organic stuff
這是有機的東西
I think there will be Dr.
我想等會有博士
can explain to us
可以跟我們解釋
there is carbon in it
有個碳在裡面
So the structures you see have nothing to do with a single carbon
所以看到的這些結構都跟一個碳沒有關係
But his research is now a very emerging direction
但是他的研究現在是一個很新興的一個方向
It is the combination of electronic components and biomedicine
是電子元件跟生物醫學的結合
we're going to talk about organic bioelectronics
我們要談一下有機生物電子
These two were a very
這兩個是當年是一個非常
Nor does it mean that in the past in the past, it was a
也不是說當年在以往在傳統的化學上是一個
Separate and independent fields
比較分開很獨立的領域
two separate domains
兩個獨立的領域
But in recent decades
但是最近在近幾十年
Slowly we know that many things have become a combination of cross-fields
慢慢的我們知道很多東西都變成了跨領域的結合
there will be some new developments
會產生一些新的發展
So in English, you can see that this is Oberonic Power Electronics
所以英文大家可以看到這邊是Oberonic Power Electronics
so a very emerging field
所以一個非常新興的領域
It's not like there's been a lot of research in this area
那也不是在這方面有很大的研究上
Some of the leading positions above
上面的一些領先的地位
he has recently
他曾經得過最近
In last year 2016
在去年2016年
Won our Academy's Young Scholar Research Writing Award
得了我們本院的年輕學者研究著作獎
Also won the Mr. Wu Dayou Memorial Award from the Ministry of Science and Technology
也拿了科技部的吳大尤先生紀念獎
This is to reward young researchers
這是為了獎勵年輕的研究人員的
the most important award
最重要的一個獎項
In the Chinese Chemical Society also took
在中國化學學會也拿了
Contact Seven Chemistry Awards
接觸七名化學獎
Accept the invitation of the Japanese Judiciary Corporation Gaofeng Sub-society
接受日本裁判法人高峰子學會邀請
International Young Scientist Award
擔任國際年輕科學家獎座
behind
後面還有
in that year
在當年
Before going to college, it used to be
還沒有進大學之後曾經是
Well, Han Yao Titi used to be
好,漢堯提提當年曾經是
International Olympia gold medal for high school students
高中生的國際奧林匹亞金牌
gold medal in chemistry
化學方面的金牌
So he's doing really well in medical studies and research.
所以他在醫療求學跟研究相當出色
but do the math
但也算算看
A representative of our young and promising Academia Sinica
我們年輕有為中研院的代表後期之秀
but
但是
His speech today is mainly in this aspect
他的今天的演講主要是在這個方面
It is what we have seen in this introduction
是我們在這個簡介大家也看到說
These turned out to be two different fields
這原來是兩個不同的領域
Because in the past in electronic components
因為以往在電子元件
Let's take a look inside your own iPhone
我們看看你自己的 iPhone 裡面
All those components are inorganic
那些所有的那些元件都是無機的
Because there are many semiconductor
因為有很多半導體系
or other metals
或者是其他的那些金屬
make that link in it
在裡面做那個連結的
It's almost an inorganic world
都是幾乎是都是無機的世界
What about organic chemistry?
那在有機化學裡面呢
We know from some of the more traditional areas of the original
我們知道從原來的一些比較傳統的領域
Also slowly develop this way
也慢慢的往這邊發展
So we probably also heard
所以我們大概也聽到說
in the news or in newspapers and magazines
在新聞裡頭或者在報章雜誌
I have heard that organic light-emitting diodes
有聽到說有機發光二級體
or organic transistor
或者是有機電晶體
and organic solar cells
還有有機太陽能電池
so in these
所以在這些
in electronic components
電子元件中
also give us a new direction
也給我們一個新的方向
So in two very distinct areas like this
所以在這樣子兩個非常獨特的領域
We're going to put it together now
我們現在要把它結合在一起
so today
所以今天
I don't do too much now
我現在不要做太多的
wasting too much of everyone's time
耽誤大家太多的時間
So Dr. Yau will tell us
所以又博士會告訴我們
These two are how we connect
這兩個是我們怎麼樣去做連結
After connecting
連結之後
it will take us in some new directions
它會帶給我們一些新的方向
have what
有什麼
make us feel very hopeful
讓我們非常覺得非常期望
Then there are some directions for great development in the future
然後將來有很大發展的一些方向
so we welcome our speakers today
所以我們歡迎我們今天的演講者
Dr. You Xiuhua
游秀華博士
Thank you, Vice President Zhou, for your introduction
謝謝周副院長的介紹
I would also like to thank you all for coming here today.
那我也非常謝謝大家今天來這邊
listen to me
聽我來
Introduce this new field
為大家介紹這一個新的領域
then i think
那我想
Because actually when I was preparing
因為其實我在準備的時候
I'm actually a little apprehensive
我其實是有一點忐忑的
because i don't know
因為我不太清楚
there are two things
有兩個事情
that's because
就是因為
The main international homestay is
民宿主要國際就是
Host Dang Er told me this
主辦當二告訴我說這個
speeches can have a wide range
演講的範圍可能很廣
the audience is very wide
就是聽眾的範圍很廣
In addition, it seems that there is a live broadcast now
加上現在好像有直播
in this way
這樣子
so i'm not sure who will hear
所以我不確定誰會聽得到
At least my son told me before I went out
最起碼我出門前我兒子還跟我講
He will watch my live
他會看我的直播
So if I'm going to say something he can understand
所以我如果要講到他聽得懂的話
it might be a little hard work
可能會有一點辛苦
my son is ten years old
對 我兒子十歲
But I want to be with today I take this opportunity
但是我想要跟今天我就接這個機會
I think I'll try to be able to
我想我會從我盡量能夠
Hope to understand
希望能夠深入淺出的
I will introduce this new field
會大家介紹這一個新的領域
Then I may spend more time on the introduction
那我可能會花比較多時間在介紹的方面
I hope that everyone can understand this field
那希望大家能夠對這個領域
have a little concept
稍微有一點概念
My premise is that you probably haven't heard of this field
我的前提假設是大家可能都沒有聽過這個領域
So if you've heard the field
所以如果你已經聽過這個領域
or know something
或是了解一些的話
That
那
i'm sorry over there
我在那邊說聲抱歉
Because there may be some things for people
因為可能有些東西對人來講
may be simpler
可能會比較簡單
But I think in such an information imagination
但是我覺得在這樣的一個資訊想像中
I would like to share with you
我願意跟大家分享
Start this series of stories from the beginning
從頭開始這一連串的故事
that's also very
那也非常
Also very grateful to the Central News Bureau
也非常感謝中央新聞局
let me in 2014
讓我在2014年的時候
Able to return to Taiwan to serve
能夠回台灣來服務
Then the continuation is
然後繼續的就是
Serving the country like this
為國效力這樣子
then i
那我
just
剛剛
Vice President Zhou has already mentioned
周副院長已經提到了
that is
就是說
traditionally speaking
在傳統上來講
naturally
自然呢
the greatest one
最偉大的一個
What about the creation?
創造物呢
that is
就是
various creatures
各式各樣的生物
all kinds of creatures
就是各式各樣的生物
you see it's a creature
你看到這是一個生物
that human
那人類
Actually humans say
其實人類說
Truth is the greatest creation
實話有個最偉大的創造物
in the most recent
在最近的
throughout the 20th century
整個20世紀以來
The main creation is
最主要創造物就是
so-called electronic components
所謂的電子元件
These two things are actually
這兩個東西其實
On the face of it
在表面上來講
It seems irrelevant
看起來是風馬牛不相及
because they have many
因為他們有很多
difference in nature
性質上的差異
there are many in
也有很多在
especially on scale
尤其是在scale上
you can know
你可以知道
people
人
at least one person is
至少一個人就是
150 cm
150公分
to 200 cm
到200公分之間
Most of them fall in this range
大部分的那是落在這個區間
An electronic component is called seven nanometers according to the latest manufacturing process of Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company.
一個電子元件按照台灣機體電路公司最新的製程叫做七奈米
It is a whole scale is completely different
它是整個的一個scale是完全不一樣的
It will have a scale mismatch
它會有一個scale的mismatch
Then from our material point of view
然後從我們材料的角度來看
You can feel that in terms of materials, human beings are a soft substance
大家可以發覺到材料上來講人是一個軟的物質
Your body is not a hard gang you are not a steel seat substance
你的身體不是硬幫幫的你不是一個鋼鐵座的物質
But most electronic components are made of hard materials
但是大部分的電子元件用的都是硬材料
Contains fine materials containing a wide variety of so-called III-V elements
包含細 包含各式各樣所謂的三五族元素的材料
There are even materials containing various oxides
甚至有包含各種的氧化物的材料
These are hard materials
這些都是硬材料
And if we analyze more deeply
而且如果大家更深入的分析
Humans are basically organic matter
人基本上是屬於有機物質
All wafers are mostly inorganic substances
所有的晶片大部分都是屬於無機物質
The cost of organic matter and its main component is carbon
有機物質它的主要的組成的成本就是碳
and not only carbon
而且不但是碳
And the most important thing we talk about in terms of opportunities is
而且在有機遇上我們最主要講的是
Carbon composed of co-driving chains
由共駕鏈組合成的碳
Promise matter is mainly formed from various accumulations of atoms
無極物質主要是從原子各式各樣的堆積
pile up into a hard material
堆積成一個硬的材料
so what
所以呢
The two substances are very different in nature
這兩個物質本質上有非常大的差異
then let's think again
然後我們再來想一想
It's a question of conductivity
就是導電的問題
everyone knows just
大家知道剛好
recently my son
最近我兒子
i mentioned my son again
我再次提到我兒子
You may hear me mention my son all the time
你們可能會一直聽到我提到我兒子
Because in fact, I often make metaphors
因為其實我很常常要做比喻
Then my son just happened to be in the fourth grade of elementary school recently.
那我兒子最近剛好是小學四年級
Just about to learn electricity
剛好要學電了
Just in the fourth grade of elementary school
剛好小學四年級
Immediately the fourth class will learn electricity
馬上第四課就要學電
because i want to teach him
因為我要教他
so i know
所以我都知道
So he's just about to learn electricity
所以他剛好要學電了
but the first thing
可是第一個事情
We all know that the human body conducts electricity.
大家都知道人體是會導電的
Conductivity of the human body
人體的導電
But with the conduction of electronic components
但是跟電子元件的導電
it's a completely different probability
它是完全不同的機率
The conduction of the human body is a very complex system
人體的導電是一個非常複雜的系統
in comparison
相較而言
Conductivity of electronic components
電子元件的導電
nothing but electrons
無非是由電子
or electric
或者是電動
Move on the circuit, this I think most people
電路上移動,這個我想大部分人
will have a little bit of basic concepts
都會有一點點基本的概念
electronics or circuits
就電子或電道
There is a basic move on the original road with a collective
帶個集體原路上有個基本的一個移動
So, it's two first, the material itself that conducts electricity
所以呢,它兩個第一個,導電的本身的物質
not the same
也不一樣
In this complex system, I will explain in a moment
在這個複雜系統中,我等下稍微再解釋
Let me explain to you in detail, it mainly comes from the transmission of some ions
跟大家解釋詳細一點,主要是來自一些離子的傳遞
Include
包含
uh gai ion
呃,蓋離子
Contains false ions , Contains that ion
包含假離子,包含那離子
And even these have some so-called neurotransmitters
甚至這些還有一些所謂的神經傳導物質
New-On Transmitter
New-On Transmitter
What does acetylcholine contain in these
包含什麼acetylcholine這些的
substance
物質
that, the last is
那,最後的是
The human body is a dynamic system
人的這個體是一個動態的系統
The so-called dynamic means
所謂的動態就是說
We grow up from small to large, your scale is always getting bigger
我們從小長到大,你的scale是一直在變大的
None of us are born with such a big scale
我們沒有人生下來,一生下來就是那麼大的一個scale
So it's a dynamic system
所以它是一個動態的系統
And then, when you're getting older, you're going to age
然後,等到你慢慢的年紀大了,你會衰老
So the whole system will also enter a decay state
所以整個系統也會進入一個decay的狀態
It includes Agent, including some reasons for aging
就包含Agent,包含老化的一些原因
that this
那這個
The chip itself is a very steady state
這個chip 本身它是一個很定態的
We make semiconductor components
我們做半導體元件
the most important thing is to say
最重要的就是說
How many times can you use this semiconductor
你這個半導體可以用多少次
how many times can switch
可以開關多少次
can switch can
可以switch 可以
Applicable
可以應用的
how long can your life be
可以你的壽命可以有多長
the best
最好的
Semiconductor life is infinite
半導體壽命都是無限
because they encapsulated it
因為他們把它封裝起來後
In fact, it can be used for a long time
其實都可以用非常久
So these two things are actually different in nature.
所以這兩個東西其實是有本質上的差異
then we
那我們
But
可是
certainly
當然
When the wisdom of nature meets the wisdom of man
大自然的智慧碰上人類的智慧的時候
Finally we want to do one thing
最後我們就會想要做一件事
just put it together
就是把它結合在一起
that when combined
那在結合在一起的時候
there will be one
就會有一個
Materially
物質上
a difference in material
材料上的一個差異性
so how do we tie it together
所以我們要怎麼把它結合在一起呢
This is what I want to share with you today
這就是我今天我要跟大家稍微分享一個題目
is how to use
就是如何利用
so-called organic conductive substances
所謂的有機導電物質
to make such a combination
來做這樣的一個結合
certainly
當然
what will happen in the future
將來會發生什麼
we are not sure
我們不確定
organic
有機
What electronic components can cause
電子元件會導致什麼樣的
future but
未來但是
Sometimes we're not sure, but Hollywood is sure
有些時候我們不確定,但是好萊塢很確定
The film industry is very powerful, he will tell us what will happen next
電影業非常的厲害,他都會告訴我們,下一步會發生什麼
For example, when your people can start to control
譬如說,當你的人可以開始控制
When using chips to control external machinery
藉由晶片,控制外面的機械的時候
you just...
你就...
You may appear like RoboCop, RoboCop
你就有可能的出現像機器戰警這樣子,RoboCop
It's a possibility that you can control machines outside with just your brain
這是一個可能性,你可以只用你的腦去控制外面的機器
Turn the signal of the nerves of your human brain into the signal of an electronic component
把你人腦的神經的訊號變成一個電子元件的訊號
send out , then go to control the machine
送出去,然後去控制機器
Of course, if one day machines want to control people
當然,如果哪一天機器想要控制人
Then the possible situation will be like Magix
那可能的狀況就會像Magix一樣
We humans become mechanical batteries
我們人就變成了機械的電池
Like a hacker character, say that people in the future don't need you to think
像駭客人物一樣,說將來人不需要你思考了
Mechanical thinking ability is stronger than yours, I didn't believe it before
機械的思考能力比你強,我以前不相信
but since the defeat of afghanistan this...
但是自從阿富汗打敗的這個...打敗的期間
We actually ran into some colleagues from the Information Office last time.
我們其實上次碰到一些資訊所的同事
He said we're all rethinking who gets to make the decisions
他說我們都在重新考慮到底誰可以做決定
so this is an interesting question that I think
所以這是一個我覺得這是一個很有趣的問題
Is it a machine controller or a human controlling the machine?
到底是機械控制員還是人控制機械
Of course we want humans to control the machines
我們當然希望是人控制機械
No matter which scenario needs an interface
不管是哪一個scenario都需要一個介面
How do you transfer energy out of the body
你怎麼把能量從人體傳出去
How to make the so-called electrical signals and these biological signals of your body
怎麼讓所謂的電訊號跟你身體的這些生物訊號
produces an appropriate conversion
產生一個適當的轉換
This is the ultimate goal of organic bioelectronics
這個就是有機生物電子最終極的目的
We want to have a very efficient conversion
我們希望有一個很efficient的轉換
There is a clear conversion
有一個很清楚的轉換
OK, let me mention it a little more
OK那我再稍微的提一下
In fact, everyone, I have been interested in this research very early.
大家其實我對這個研究興趣其實是很早的
I've always found it funny since I probably started in graduate school
我大概從研究所開始的時候就一直覺得很有趣
Because everyone knows, of course, on the one hand, we are from Taiwan
因為大家知道當然一方面是我們來自台灣
Taiwan is the Kingdom of Semiconductors
台灣是半導體王國
Taiwan is electronic components
台灣就是電子元件
most famous country
最有名的國家
Every one of my classmates is in TSMC
我的同學每一個都在台積電
Then each of them left TSMC
然後也每一個都離開台積電
Because they all went to start a company
因為他們都去開公司了嘛
So everyone has been to TSMC
所以每一個都待過台積電
Each one leaves TSMC
每一個都離開台積電
But Taiwan's electronic components
但是台灣的電子元件
With such a strong strength
這麼強的實力的情況下
Now it has also entered the so-called Hon Hai of electronic components
現在也進入了所謂電子元件的鴻海
very early on i started thinking
很早的時候我就開始在想
Where is the next South China Sea?
那下一個南海在哪裡
just say we certainly can't
就說我們當然不可能
Just start over and restart a stove
就重新開始重啟一個爐灶
Where might the next South China Sea for electronic components be?
那電子元件的下一個南海可能在哪裡
so i always feel like saying
所以我一直覺得說
Then shall we just
那我們是不是乾脆就
Let's say you made a nice transistor
比如說你做了一個很好的電晶體
You can put the transistor
你可以把電晶體
Just insert it directly into the human body to control the human body
就直接塞到人體裡面去控制人體
what kind of difficulties it will encounter
它會碰到什麼樣的困難
In fact, when I first entered the Ph.
其實在剛進博士班的時候
i had this idea
我就有這樣的想法
but i always feel
可是我一直覺得
My boss won't approve the first one
第一個我老闆不會准
The second one seems a bit risky
第二個是好像有點冒險
I can't find anyone to plug, so I can't plug myself
我找不到人可以塞,那總不能塞自己吧
Right, so we want to say
對不對,所以我們想說
I was thinking about something like this, but
就在想這樣的一個事情,但是
After ten years, twenty years of thinking
經過這十年來,二十年來一直的思考
We found that the two middle actually
我們發覺到說,這兩個中間實際上
there is a difference
是有一個不一樣的地方
You can imagine, the traditional electronic components, what kind of characteristics it has
你可以想像,傳統的電子元件,它有什麼樣的特性
Traditional electronic components are made of hard materials
傳統的電子元件是用硬的材料
All of these materials are required to be stable in the air
這些材料我們都要要求是,在空氣中要穩定
Of course, many electronic components have to be unstable in the air
當然很多電子元件才要在空氣中不穩定
But we use a very precise method to package it up
可是我們用的很精密的手法,把它包裝起來
package it up
把它packaging起來
So there are many good raw packaging factories in Taiwan
所以台灣有很多很好的生裝廠
Then after packaging, the life of these electronic components can be very long
然後packaging以後,這些電子元件的壽命就可以很長
Then most of the applied one
然後大部分應用的一個
For one application, the so-called process status is the so-called
應用的一個,所謂的製程的狀況是所謂的
CO, is a vapor deposition
CO,是一個vapor deposition
is a chemical vapor deposition
是一個chemical vapor deposition
It is a way to use, to use the frame rate
是一個就是利用,利用幀度的方式
Use the gas frame method to go
利用氣體幀度的方式去
then what we need
然後我們需要的是什麼
What we need is that this system is very robust
我們需要的是這個系統非常的 robust
For example, if you want to buy a TV
比如你做買一台電視
you bought a computer
你買了一個電腦
Of course you wish you could use it for the rest of your life
你當然希望你能夠用一輩子
Although your manufacturer may not want you to use it for a lifetime
雖然你的製造商可能不希望你用一輩子
But the person you buy expects him to use for a lifetime
但是你買的人希望他用一輩子
Then
然後
at last
最後
This may be a bit more controversial
這個可能比較 controversial 一點
but actually
但是實際上
for
對於
In terms of toxicity
毒性來講
Our requirement is actually full minimum
我們的要求其實是滿 minimum
Just don't be toxic to the environment
就是你不要對環境有毒
Don't be toxic to the environment when you shoot this thing
你拍這東西不要對環境有毒
Then the material used is actually
然後用的材料其實
We all know the materials used to make semiconductors
大家都知道半導體製成用的材料
Impossible not poisonous
不可能沒毒
just use light folic acid
光是用個輕佛酸
Everyone is free to check
大家可以有空去查看
What kind of poison is folic acid
輕佛酸是怎麼樣的毒物
What kind of poison is the Buddha's gas used?
這些用的佛的氣體是怎麼樣的毒物
It is quite toxic
它都是有相當大的毒性
but of course we can
但是我們當然我們可以
We apply sophisticated
我們應用精密的
mechanical manipulation
機械的操控
mechanical engineering techniques
機械的工程手法
We can maintain it in an environment
我們可以把它維持在一個環境中
don't let it poison
不要讓它去產生毒害
but essentially use
但是本質上用的東西
is poisonous
是有毒的
but
但是
Because this program is very good
因為這個程序非常的好
Then lead to so much output value in Taiwan
然後導致在台灣產生了這麼多的產值
Of course it also led us
當然也導致了我們
I didn't see many young people at the scene, but
現場我沒有看到比較多的年輕人不過
Just heard the news that
剛剛聽到一個消息就是說
Nowadays, young people are more and more fond of
現在的年輕人越來越多喜歡
don't miss Dr.
就不想念博士
Because it is very profitable to go to TSMC
因為去台積電很好賺
but of course
可是當然
Taiwan's economy has made considerable contributions
這個台灣的經濟是有相當大的貢獻
I don't deny it at all
我一點都不否認
but i can only say
但是我只能說
Such a process is
這樣的一個過程都
He does have a different way of thinking and an idea
他的確是有不同的一個思維跟一個想法
But when anything you come into contact with living organisms
但是當任何一個東西你接觸到生物體的時候
Let's see what it might need
我們看看它可能有什麼樣的需要
first in bioelectronics
首先在生物電子上
Generally speaking, what we want is soft matter
一般來講我們希望的是軟物質
why soft matter
為什麼是軟物質
I often make a metaphor for everyone
我常常做一個比喻給大家聽
Of course, I always feel that my metaphor is very bad.
當然這個比喻我一向覺得我的比喻很不好
But let's just listen
不過大家就姑且聽知
Just a question for everyone
就是很問大家一個問題
do you like to sleep or
你喜歡睡應場還是
Hard bed or soft bed?
硬床還是睡軟床嘛
Most people like to sleep on a soft Tuanwang bed
大部分人都喜歡睡軟的團王床
Hard bed but wouldn't you want to sleep on a plank
硬床但是你不會想睡木板嘛
I'm not saying
我說的不是
For organisms
對於生物體來講
Thin wafers are not just boards
細晶片不但是木板
And it's a cold marble floor
而且是冰冰涼涼的大理石地板
very bad sleep
非常的不好睡
So any biochip
所以任何一個生物晶片上面
If you're going to have a meeting with a creature
如果你要有跟生物做見面
It actually prefers soft matter
它其實比較喜歡的是軟物質
just a bit soft
就是有一點像軟的
Whether it is hydrogel, Hydrogel
不管是水凝膠、Hydrogel
or how
或是怎麼樣
what it likes is a soft substance
它喜歡的是一個軟物質
In addition to being stable in the air, it
那它除了空氣中要穩定外
The most important thing is to be stable in the water
最重要的是水中要穩定
Because the most abundant of all living organisms is water
因為所有的生物體中含的最多的就是水
You have to have water stability
你必須要有水的穩定度
Okay, let's think about the stability of the water again.
好我們再來想想看水的穩定度
Words on the stability of our water
對我們的水的穩定度的話
This is for traditional e-liquid
這個對傳統的電子液來講
indeed a challenge
的確就是個挑戰
right
對不對
We often see all kinds of people on the Internet
我們常常在網路上看到各式各樣的人
The PO article said that the iPhone got water accidentally today
PO文說不小心今天iPhone進水了
then it's over
然後就完了
right so let's think about it
對不對 所以我們想想看說
The main thing is your stability in the water
最主要是你在水中的穩定度
and you made this
而且你做的這個
The entire process is best made with easy
整個的製程最好是用容易來製成
because it is easy to make
因為容易製成中
You can use many polymer materials
你可以用到很多高分子的材料
So my polymer materials cannot be stacked by vaporization
所以我高分子的材料是不能夠用氣化堆積的
must come with water
必須要用水像的來
must be handled with easy images
必須要用容易像來處理
and then the other one is
然後另外一個是
in bioelectronics
在生物電子中
If your material is too balanced or too durable
你這個材料如果太兼顧或太耐用
It's not necessarily a good thing
其實不見得是個好事
Because sometimes we want this material to be biodegradable
因為有的時候我們希望這個材料是能夠生物降解
That is to say, when it has completed its mission
也就是說當它完成了它的使命之後
organisms will automatically decompose it
生物體會自動的把它分解
In this way, the compounding of nature and your body will be less
這樣對自然對你身體的複合都會變少
So the last thing that matters most is
所以最後一個事情最重要的是
This toxicity is in bioelectronics
這個毒性是在生物電子中
is a very large concentration because you have to be in direct contact with your body
是非常大的concent 因為你必須要直接接觸你的人體
From a scientific point of view
從科學的角度上來講
He has to touch your body
他必須要接觸你的人體
So we have to have very, very low toxicity
所以我們必須這個毒性要非常非常的低
from an economic point of view
那從經濟上的角度來講
Because you have to pass the FDA
因為你要過FDA
you have to go through regulation
你要過regulation
You have to go through all the legal institutions to circumvent
你要過所有的規避的法律的機構
You have to have compliance biotoxicity
你必須要有符合的生物毒性
Otherwise you have no way to go public
否則你沒有辦法上市
you can't turn it into a product
你沒有辦法變成產品
You can't generate market value
你沒有辦法產生市場價值
this is all in
這個都是在
so-called once inside the biological element
所謂的一旦進到生物元件中
Problems that traditional electronic components must face
傳統的電子元件必定會面對的問題
So let me do a simple analysis with you first
所以我先跟大家做一個簡單的分析後
I hope everyone has a clear statement
我希望大家有個明瞭說
Traditional Inorganic Materials
傳統的無機材料
maybe need an up
或許需要一個up
need an upgrade need an upgrade
需要一個提升需要一個upgrade
for use in bioelectronics
來用到生物電子上面
That
那
the opposite
那相反的
in chemistry
在化學中
Because I still study chemistry
因為我還是學化學
Although many people think that I don’t seem to be doing chemistry recently
雖然最近很多人覺得我不太像在做化學
But my former university teacher is here
可是我以前大學的老師在這裡
so i have to say i still study chemistry
所以我必須要說我還是學化學
So traditional chemistry
所以傳統的化學
Usually, there are two types of materials
通常就是分成兩類材料
organic materials
一類叫做有機材料
Inorganic materials
一類叫無機材料
that organic material was stigmatized for a while
那有機材料有一陣子被污名化
Now it's more advanced
現在又變高級化
Because organic food is more expensive
因為有機食物都賣得比較貴
So the word organic has become very advanced again
所以有機這個字又變成很高級
for a while organic wasn't great
有一陣子有機變得不太好
that's it
就是這樣子
so in terms of dialogue
所以對話來講
The definition of organic for us is very simple
有機對我們來講的定義非常簡單
Organic is a structure based on carbon
有機就是以碳為主的一個架構
then formed
然後形成的
Focus on co-driving
以共駕建為主
some compounds or molecules that form
形成的一些的化合物或分子
Inorganic is everything except carbon
無機就是除了碳以外的所有的人
is inorganic
就是無機
so but
所以但是
Traditionally, everyone knows organic, and what everyone knows best about organic is plastic
傳統來講,大家都知道有機,有機大家最清楚的就是塑膠
We usually deal with plastic, plastic, think about it
我們平常弄弄的是塑膠,塑膠,大家想一想
Thinking about it from the brain, plastic, plastic does not conduct electricity
從腦筋來想,塑膠,塑膠不會導電啊
right , we learn anything
對不對,我們學任何的
Whether it is middle school or high school, we will be the first to say that plastics do not conduct electricity
不管是國中、高中,我們都會第一個學說塑膠不導電
Plastic is a flying conductor
塑膠是一個飛導體
Traditionally, the decomposition of organic and inorganic
傳統來講,有機跟無機的分解也是
organics are flying conductors, then inorganic compounds
有機是飛導體,然後無機的化合物
There are many with metallic luster and high conductivity
有很多具有金屬光澤,具有橫高的導電性
but
但是
all the rules of chemistry
所有的化學的規則
are all
都是
formulated to be broken
制定後是用來打破的
As we enter the millennium, the Nobel Prize in Chemistry in 2000
我們在邁入千禧年的時候,2000年的化學諾貝爾獎
Most importantly to these three gentlemen
最重要的是給了這三位先生
Professor Allen Peecker,Professor Allen McDermott
Professor Allen Peecker,Professor Allen McDermott
and Professor Hidesu Shirakawa from Japan, the first two are American professors
以及日本的白川英素教授,前兩位是美國教授
them
他們
discover something together
共同發現一件事情
plastic conducts electricity
塑膠可以導電
We can make conductive plastic
我們可以做出導電的塑膠
Well, I think today I'm going to take a little time to tell you about this story.
那我想今天我要花一點點時間跟大家介紹一下這個故事
Because the research I did for this story was
因為這個故事跟我做的研究是
it's the whole beginning
算是整個開始
This whole new field of
這整個一個新的領域的
a bad wound
一個爛傷
That's why my field as a whole started booming
也就是為什麼我這個領域整個開始蓬勃發展
Whether it is organic electronics
不管是有機電子
no matter how
不管是
Next Organic Bioelectronics
接下來的有機生物電子
I can only say
我只能說
All our research is standing
我們所有的研究都是站在
Seniors stand on the shoulders of these giants to see the world
前輩站在這些巨人的肩膀上去看這個世界
we didn't start from scratch
我們並不是從無到有
We are all the result of following others
我們都是跟著人家的結果
So we've taken a look for you
所以我們為大家採取了一下
All Nobel said that the Nobel words of two thousand years were awarded to these three
都諾貝爾講兩千年諾貝爾話講是頒給這三位
Mainly found to say
主要是發現到說
There is a kind of conductive polymer called
有一種叫做導電的高分子
From whitening to complete, it is conductive plastic
從白化一點的完整就是導電的塑膠
plastic is conductive
是塑膠是可以導電的
that's why
那到底是為什麼
I will give you some simple analysis
我給大家做一些簡單的一些分析
today so far
今天到目前為止
actually
其實
I'm quite proud
我還蠻自豪的
But so far I haven't put any chemistry room
但目前為止我還沒有放上任何一個化學室
He knows that those who study chemistry will definitely get a bachelor of chemistry
他知道念化學的人一定會放上化學士
I'm sorry, I'm going to put Chem now.
那很抱歉我現在要放上化學士
Before that, let me tell you
在這之前我先跟大家講
Because I was still a student when I was able to speak for two thousand years
因為兩千年都會講的時候我還當學生
so in two thousand zero this should be two thousand zero
所以在兩千零這應該是兩千零
In 2003 or 2003 in a
二或零三年的時候在一個
Annual Meeting of the American Chemical Society
美國化學會的年會上
i was lucky to hear
我很有幸的聽到了
Lecture by Professor Ellen McDermott
Ellen McDermott教授的演講
And he's actually a really nice guy
然後他其實他是一個非常好的人
He's also a guy who likes to show off very much
他也是一個非常喜歡炫耀的人
So he put his Nobel medal over there for everyone to take pictures
所以他就把他Nobel獎牌放在那邊給大家照相
So you can take pictures if you want
所以要照的都可以去照
Of course I think it should be true
當然我想應該是真的啦
Shouldn't be shipping
應該不是用運品
So we based on a student's instinct
所以我們基於一個學生的本能
Just have something to take care of
就是有東西一定要照
You must punch in the photo
照了一定要打卡
no
不是
Although I didn't check in
雖然我沒有打卡
But there must have been such a thing as punching cards in those days.
但是那個年代一定有打卡這個事情
Then you can see
然後就可以看到
This is a photo of the Nobel Prize for two thousand years
這個是兩千年的Nobel獎的照片
Although at that time everyone can realize
雖然那個時候可以大家可以發覺到
The camera at that time was 2 megapixels
那個時候的那個照相機是兩百萬像素的
So this is a bit unclear
所以這個比較不清楚一點
OK, let's tell you a little bit about this story
OK,我們跟大家稍微講解一下這個故事
This story is actually a
這個故事其實是一個
To me it's actually a pretty
對我而言其實是一個蠻
pretty inspiring story
蠻 inspiring 的故事
That is to say, when we are doing scientific research in chemical research
也就是說我們在做化學研究的科學研究的時候
In fact, this story came from a complete mistake.
其實這個故事完全是來自於一個錯誤
I will introduce this error
我會大家介紹這個錯誤
Then we start with crude oil
然後我們從原油開始講
Everyone knows polymers
大家都知道高分子
that is, plastic
也就是塑膠
most famous of plastics
塑膠中最有名的
This is what is called Juyixi
就是這一個東西叫做聚以溪
Taiwan also produces a lot
台灣也產了很多
Juyixi
聚以溪
In chemistry, we do it by taking Yixi
在化學上我們做方法就是把以溪
this monomer
這個單體
make it a
把它做一個
polyyixi
聚合物的聚合後就變成聚以溪
That
那
Such a process, of course
這樣一個過程當然
Yixi is better now than his brother
以溪現在好一點比他的兄弟要
quite a bit
蠻有一點
Because his brother's name is Bingxi
因為他的兄弟叫秉溪
Bingxi is quite notorious now.
秉溪現在蠻惡名糟糟的
Because it's notorious since Ma Kaohsiung bombed
因為自從馬高雄炸了以後就很惡名糟糟
What about his gas?
他這些氣體呢
Polymers can then become Polymers
然後可以聚合物就變成聚以蜥
Then if we use some
那我們如果利用某一些
Catholist
Catholist
with some coarser
用一些粗化物
Especially do what we call Cigernata Catis
尤其做我們叫做 Cigernata Catis
Of course Cigernata Catis is another Nobel Prize
當然 Cigernata Catis 又是另外一個 Nobel 獎
This is the 1963 Nobel Prize
這是1963年 Nobel 獎
someone found out
有人發現了
How to use lizards to make high value
如何利用以蜥做成很高價值
very tall great polyether material
很高 很棒的聚以蜥的材料
these two
這兩位
Cigur discovered this together with Nata
Cigur 跟 Nata 共同發現這個事情
because of its strong economic value
因為有具有很強大的經濟價值
So that's why later
所以就是為什麼後來
Plastic has become a very dominant material in the world
塑膠變成全世界一個很dominion的材料原因
Because we have discovered many new ways in the village
因為在村化界我們發現了很多新的方式
Capable of making very high value polylizards
能夠做出很高價值的聚以蜥
that in chemistry in science
那在化學界 在科學界
people are quick to think
人們就很快就去想說
So what can Cigernata Catis start doing
那Cigernata Catis 開始能夠做什麼
So in 1955 to 1960 can start
所以在1955年到1960年就能開始
use
用
one of lizards
以蜥的一個
a compound of a brother
算是一個兄弟的一個化合物
lizard
叫做以蜥
want to aggregate it
想要聚合它
poly-lizard
就形成一個那個聚以蜥
see if there is
看有沒有
something like this happens
有這樣的東西發生
That 195.12.6 says
那195.12.6年說
many people send
很多人都發
some people reported that
有些人報導說
According to lack of discovery
據缺有發現
But what they found missing was a
可是他們發現的據缺是一個
black powder
黑色的粉末
That
那
I just mentioned three professors
我剛剛有提到三位教授
Professor Na Shirakawa
那白川英素教授
At that time he had just started his research career
那個時候剛開始他的研究生涯
he
他
just want to try this experiment
就想要去嘗試這個實驗
to learn about this experiment
去了解這個實驗
what about this time
那在這個時候呢
some day
某一天
He was with a Korean student
他跟一個韓國的學生
found to say
發現到說
Eh
欸
he reacts the same way
他一樣做這個反應
he found out that
他發現到說
Eh
欸
how did he get one
他怎麼得到一個
A film with a metallic luster
具有金屬光澤的一個薄膜
what happened
到底發生什麼事
so what
所以呢
words in the lab
在實驗室的話
i think we
我想我們
presence if
在場如果
probably many are
可能很多是
the ancestors of the Central Academy
中央院的先輩
I may also have domestic scholars
我也可能也有國內的學者
we see this problem
我們看到這樣問題
Of course we're going back and checking our lab notes
我們當然是回去檢查我們的實驗筆記
see bottom
看到底
What went wrong
出了什麼問題
they found one thing
他們就發現一件事情
Oops, they made the most of chemists
糟糕,他們犯了化學家最
worst mistake
最不該犯的錯誤
It's just that they miscalculated the equivalent
就是他們把當量算錯了
That is to say, when they write, they put
也就是說他們在寫的時候,他們把
It is possible to put minimolar mini
可能把minimolar的mini
change, forget, mm
換,忘了,毫米
millet
毫磨的毫
forgot
忘掉了
So they used a thousand times
所以他們用了一千倍
Equivalent
當量的
Chemicals
抽化劑
Use a very large amount of deodorant
用了非常大當的抽化劑
So the reaction is very fast
所以反應非常的快
It only takes a minute or two for the film to form
只要一、兩分鐘這個薄膜就產生
very fast
非常的快
This is completely different from previous reports
這跟以前的報導完全的不一樣
so of course
所以當然啊
What happens next is even more special
接下去的事情就更特別
generally speaking
就一般來講
Sometimes we find that
有時候我們發現說
especially
尤其是
We don't see too many students on site
我們現場看不到太多學生
sometimes, but maybe
有時候,不過或許
There are students live
直播有學生
Sometimes students see something wrong
有時候學生看到錯的東西就會
I feel like, ah, what's wrong?
覺得說,啊錯了怎麼辦
wash him off , don ' t tell the teacher
把他洗掉,千萬不要告訴老師
Otherwise, maybe the teachers will scold me
不然的話,可能老師們會罵我
in this way
這樣子
But something is wrong
可是其實錯的東西
Sometimes, will give you some new
有的時候,會給你一些新的
Often many scientific discoveries
常常很多的科學的發現
in such an error
就是在這樣一個錯誤中
produce a beautiful result
造成一個美麗的結果
So when they found this metallic luster
所以他們發現這個金屬光澤的時候
Actually quite excited
其實還蠻興奮的
just found out
就發現說
Hey, what the hell is this thing?
欸 這個東西到底是什麼
just at this time
這時候剛好
He later discovered this in 1967
後來他在1967年的時候發現這個事情
until 1975
一直到1975年的時候
the second of these
其中的第二位這個
Professor Nadelman
乃德爾門教授
he went to japan
他到日本
At that time, Professor Baichuan Yingxiu was at Dongqing Public Health University
那個時候百川英修教授在東慶公衛大學
when he visited
他去訪問的時候
Professor Baichuan Yingxiu is discussing the result
他百川英修教授在討論這個結果
he is very excited
他非常的興奮
He immediately invited Professor Baichuan to come in 1977
他立刻邀請百川教授1977年的時候到
Excuse me
不好意思
Eh, very wrong
欸 很錯了嘛
1977 time to
1977年的時候到
arrive
到
Uh Penn
呃 賓州大學
when they were at the university of penn
那時候他們在賓州大學
to do
去做
Profession
職業
That's why they systematically discovered
所以他們才一系統性的去發現到說
turn out to be
原來
what he synthesized
他合成的東西
According to lack
據以缺
might be one of these
可能是這樣的一個
biology of a molecule
生物 一個分子的
But the structure of this molecule is not the source of the conduction
但這個分子的結構不是導電的來源
but like a semiconductor
而是像半導體一樣
When I apply some compound in the middle go
當我應用一些化合物在中間去
so-called defects
所謂的產生一些缺陷
let these all the orbitals of this molecule
讓它這些所有的這個分子的軌域
When the consensus molecular orbitals create defects
共和的分子軌域產生缺陷的時候
it produces like metal
它產生的像金屬一樣
The so-called electronic belt and driving belt
所謂的電子帶跟駕帶
The so-called Valence Band
所謂的Valence Band
A concept with Conduction Band
跟Conduction Band的一個觀念
Then they learned that
然後他們就了解到說
Where does the conductivity of atoms come from?
原子這個導電度是從何而來
According to the Shirakawa Sonic System
根據白川音速制度
It's my own autobiography
就是自己的自傳寫的
They were in the lab that day
就是他們那天在實驗室
once
一旦
When the time comes their show
到時候他們的是秀
Show gas once down after
秀的氣體一旦下去後
he noticed that
他發覺到說
Conductivity increased by a million-fold
導電度增加了100萬倍
Because the equipment at that time was very bad
因為那時候的儀器非常的不好
Just no Auto Switch
就是不會有Auto Switch
So you have to use the Menu Switch
所以你要用Menu Switch
What will be the problem if the current is suddenly too high?
電流突然太大問題會是什麼
The machine will burn
機器就燒了嘛
So they took one of their
所以他們就把他們那時候的一個
4.0 pog is burned
4.0pog就燒掉了
but anyway
但是不管怎樣
Burned a 4.0pog in exchange for a Nobel Prize
燒了一台4.0pog換來一個諾貝爾獎
i think it's worth it
我想這也是值得
ok
ok
So here is a story for you
所以這跟大家介紹一個故事
Of course this story is for us
那當然這故事對我們來講
To me, the inspiration is that
對我來講其實大家啟示是說
In fact, sometimes this thing actually
其實有的時候這個東西其實
that time
那個時候
And their first paper was published in a
而且他們第一篇paper是發在一個
A very specialized journal in chemistry is called CAMCO
化學很專門的期刊叫做CAMCO
Now many people want to talk about publishing Science
現在很多人想說要發Science
Nature
Nature
They are not posting Science
他們也不是發Science
They actually put a lot of effort into these a lot
他們是其實花很多力氣在這些很多
Very basic and Fundamental
很基本性很Fundamental的
very basic science
很基礎性的科學就上
Get some results that no one else thought of
得到一些完完全全人家都沒有想過的結果
I believe everyone in Xuehua knows that
我相信學化學人都知道說
traditional organic and inorganic
傳統有機跟無機的
A so-called boundary is broken
所謂的一條界線被打破
the first time was in
第一次是在
18 years old
18多少年的時候
The so-called Ulava
所謂的Ulava
can make green acid
可以讓青酸
hydrocyanic acid
青酸
when it becomes urea
變成尿素的時候
This is the so-called low boundary between organic and inorganic is broken
這是所謂的有機無機的界線低是打破
after
之後
When we found Fyrocyn
當我們發現到Fyrocyn
When I found Tie Erwu Wan
發現到鐵二物丸的時候
electricity is broken
有電是被打破
Then this can be said to be broken again for the third time.
那這個可以說是第三次又被打破了
Because we used to think that only metals can conduct electricity
因為以前我們覺得只有金屬可以導電
Now it is not
現在不是
Planned
有計畫物
piece of plastic
一片塑膠
it also conducts electricity
它也可以導電
and it will have different properties
而且它會有不同的性質
because it is soft matter
因為它是軟物質
is a soft substance that conducts electricity
是一個軟的物質它可以導電
OK
OK
Then I would like to take this opportunity to mention a little bit.
那我想借這個機會我也要稍微提一下
Because I just mentioned that Vice President Zhou
因為我剛剛周副院長提過
i am in japan
我在日本
The School of Physics and Chemistry has worked in the institute for six years
理化學院就所工作了六年
Actually, I know some of Shirakawa's students
其實我認識一些白川英素的學生
In fact, Professor Shirakawa Hidesu is a
其實白川英素教授是一個
very funny chemist
非常有趣的化學家
I tell you his story
我跟大家介紹他的故事
thinking about private matters
想著因為私事想
because i think i will
因為我想我就
talk about everything
什麼都講
I hope everyone can take the blame for this
希望這個大家能夠引咎一下
That is to say, Professor Hideso Shirakawa
就是說白川英素教授
actually a
其實是一個
I think, the title behind this is not written by any magazine, nor is it written by a weekly magazine. I think
我覺得啦,這個後面的這個title不是什麼雜誌寫的,也不是一週刊寫的是我想的
He's an underrated trans scientist.
就是他一個被低估的跨學家
Because he was born in Tokyo in 1936
因為他1936年出生於東京
He received a Ph.D. from Tokyo Institute of Technology, Tokyo Institute of Technology in 1966
他1966年獲得東京工業大學Tokyo Institute of Technology的博士學位
In 1967, it was discovered that lack of metal luster
1967年發現以缺,據以缺的金屬光澤
In 1976, he was a visiting researcher at the University of Pennsylvania. In 1977, they discovered that the conductive graph can be increased by 1 million times.
1976年,賓州大學訪問研究,1977年他們一起發現到導電圖可以增加100萬倍
But no one cares about this result
可是這個結果沒有人care
In 1979, under the Japanese system
79年的時候,在日本的體制下
Generally speaking, wherever you get your Ph.D., you will find ways to become an assistant professor in that laboratory
一般來講你在哪裡拿到博士學位,你就會在那個實驗室想辦法爭取成為助理教授
Associate Professor , Becoming Professor of Politics
副教授,成為政教授
But because people don't think his result is nothing
但是因為大家不覺得他的結果沒什麼
So he was forced to move from Tokyo Institute of Technology to Takesa University, where he became a professor
所以他被逼著從東京工業大學,搬到竹坡大學,在那邊變成了教授
Then in March 2000
然後到2000年的3月的時候
You can count it, that is, he is 65 years old, and he is going to retire
你可以算上看,就是他65歲了,就是要退休了
pension
領退休金了
he
他
The Japanese system is like this
日本的系統是這樣子
Maybe they are all Japanese friends
或許都是日本朋友
Well done if you call retirement
你如果叫做退休做得很好
Like Vice President Zhou
像周副院長這樣子
You can change to another place to continue your career
你可以換到另外一個地方繼續你的career
Although you have to retire where you were
雖然你在原來的地方必須要退休
but you may have to be able to go to the next place
但是你可能必須可以到下一個地方去
but
但是
no one wants him
他沒有人要他
Enough University March 2003
2003年3月足夠大學
he is basically
他基本上就是
Retire naked
裸退
I don't mean to quit naked
也不是說裸退
He took his pension
他帶著退休金退
but
但是
did not continue him
就沒有繼續他
He said my research career was over
他說我的研究生涯就此結束
And then more ironically
然後更諷刺的是
In October 2001 he won the Nobel Prize
2001年10月他得諾貝爾獎
all the schools start looking for him
所有的學校開始找他
his students told me
他的學生跟我說
he told them
他跟他們講
Back then you didn't want me
當年你們都不要我
I don't want you now
現在我也不要你們
He continues to retreat naked
他繼續裸退
he just stays on
他就留在繼續
stay in
留在
He actually did something
他其實還是有做一些事情
because i know him
因為我認識他
i know him students tell me
我認識他學生告訴我
their science museum in japan
他們他在日本的科學館
There are experiments to teach children to do conductive polymers
有教小朋友做導電高分子的實驗
He will personally explain to them
他會親自去講解給他們聽說
what is the principle of this experiment
這個實驗的原理是什麼
He is a
他是一個
Even if he was bigger than the professor last year
他就算去年大於教授得到
The Nobel Prize-winning animal that died because of cells
因為細胞致世的諾貝爾獎獸
He also came out to criticize
他也出來批評說
Today's young people don't know how to do mental science
現在的年輕人都不懂得做防得Mental Science
In fact, he has great enthusiasm for this science.
其實他對這個科學是有很大的熱情
But when
但是在
whether in japan
不管是在日本
Actually in Japan
其實在日本本地
He is also a very underrated word also called
他也都是一個很被低估的話也叫
of all nobel prizes
在所有諾貝爾獎中
No one particularly admires him
大家也沒有特別的推崇他
but
但是
I can only say he really
我只能說他真的
I to me he's really a very serious scientist
我對我而言他真的是一個非常認真的科學家
There are also many serious scientists in the Central Academy
這個在中央院中也有很多這些認真的科學家
that is
就是
we found a phenomenon
我們發現一個現象
we are willing to pursue
我們就願意去追尋
Science is supposed to be a pursuit
那科學本來就是應該是一個追尋
Sometimes you don't care what's going on outside
有時候你不要管外面要說什麼
or what others have to say
或是別人要說什麼
we just keep going
我們就是繼續去追尋
so he
所以他
i feel in
我覺得在
take advantage of
趁著
Usually I don't know how to talk about this
平常我不知道會講這個啦
but
不過
Since it is a knowledge experiment
趁著既然是知識想驗
I thought I'd share it with you
我想就跟大家分享一下
this is me
這是我
he treats me personally
他對我個人
all one
所有一個
Enlightenment and inspiration
啟示跟啟發
That is to say
也就是說
I think sometimes scientific research does not need to think too much
我覺得有時候科研就不需要去想太多
what can be used
到底可以用什麼
can it be used
到底可以用
All he actually found was an attitude
他其實發現的只有個態度
He actually didn't do it
他其實他並沒有做
what's behind
所謂後面的什麼
organic light emitting diode
有機發光二級體啊
Organic Electron
有機電經體
he didn't do it
他都沒有做
The only thing he did was understand
他只做了一件事就是了解
conductive polymer
導電高分子
why conduct electricity
為什麼會導電
He spent a lot of effort to understand this matter
他花了很多的力去去了解這件事情
Then I think this is a very important one
那我想這個是一個很重要的一個
Fundamental Science的improvement
Fundamental Science的improvement
so why
所以是為什麼
2000 will not speak
2000年都不會講
Although he is not the first to make a conductive polymer
雖然他不是第一個做出導電高分子的
but he
但是他
Share this Price with two other scientists
跟其他兩位科學家就Share這個Price
ok
ok
then i will continue
那我繼續講
Compare
比較
academic part
學術的部分
That is to say
也就是說
Of course, we first started from this so-called
當然我們最早是從這個所謂的
The shortage begins
巨缺開始
but the same structure
但是同樣的結構
Chemists are smart
化學家很聰明就會
use it in various ways
把它用各種不同的方式
to cause this
去造成這樣子
so-called co-double bond
所謂的共二雙鍵
So if you have any questions
那如果大家有任何疑問什麼
To have two double bonds is
要共二雙鍵就是
you two
你這個東西兩根
One sword is called double sword, one sword is called single sword
一根劍叫雙劍,一根劍叫單劍
That is to say, you must be two swords and one sword
也就是說,你必須是兩根劍一根劍
Two swords and one sword, two swords and one sword, lined up like this
兩根劍一根劍,兩根劍一根劍,這樣一齒的排下去
We found many different
我們發現很多不同的
There are cases where compounds contain the so-called
化合物有這樣的情況,包含所謂的
Jupiluo, two swords and one sword
聚皮落,兩根劍一根劍
two swords one sword two swords one sword two swords one sword
兩根劍一根劍,兩根劍一根劍,兩根劍一根劍
Or Jusunfen, two swords and one sword
或者是聚曬分,兩根劍一根劍
Two swords and one sword, even combined swords
兩根劍一根劍,甚至化合劍
A lot of different things are also being thought about, such as
很多不同的東西也有在想,比如說
polyanoling, it also conducts electricity
polyanoling,它也會導電
There are even some more complex
甚至還有一些比較更複雜的
Contains the so-called aggregated to... aggregated to the missing
包含所謂的聚本以...聚對本以缺
If you get together, they will also conduct electricity
跟聚對本以息,他們也會有導電的狀況
These materials are actually very important, because some of them conduct electricity
那這些材料其實都很重要,因為有些會導電
Some are now being used as optoelectronic materials
有些現在是被用作光電材料
These materials, in varying amounts, allow the field to flourish
各式量的這些材料,讓整個領域蓬勃發展
This is in chemical science
這個是在化學科學的方面
As for the application
那至於在應用的方面
I believe everyone
我相信大家
More or less have heard of these applications
或多或少都有聽過這些應用
Of course, the most famous of these is the
其中當然這個最有名的就是
OLED stands for Organic Light Emitting Diode
OLED也就是有機發光二級體
many of you now
現在很多你的
mobile phone backplane
手機的背板
We all claim to be the backplane of OLED
我們都號稱是OLED的背板
even this one
甚至這一台
this is
這個是
sorry this is korean
對不起這個是韓貨
Because Taiwan has not yet made it
因為台灣還沒有做出來
This is Korean and this is Samsung
這是韓貨這是三星的
OLED to Think TV
OLED去念電視
there is also
那另外還有
Maybe it's made so-called organic
可能就是做成所謂的有機的
Transistor
電晶體
That
那
We all know that the biggest difference between Internet material and obligation quality is
大家知道網物質跟義務質最大不同就是
We are now bendable transistors
我們現在是可以變成可以彎折的電晶體
This transistor can be bent
這個電晶體都可以彎折
Transistors that become so-called late
變成所謂的晚性的電晶體
Then this is a solar panel of the late style
然後這個是晚式的太陽的面板
Organic Solar Panels
有機太陽的面板
even if you put the transistor
甚至你把電晶體
make one with a creature
跟生物做一個
This is more like outside
這個比較像是體外
So we're not really bioelectronics
所以我們不太算是生物電子
Because bioelectronics our way is inside the body
因為生物電子我們方式是體內
But in vitro it can also be designed as
但是體外的話也可以設計成
like
比如像
An artificial hand like this
這樣子的一個人工的手
This is made by Professor Somya of the University of Tokyo
這個是東京大學的Somya教授做
These are mainly currently
這些主要是目前已經在
market or company
市面上或是公司上
Prototypes that can already be seen
已經可以看到的Portotype
When the employed person in Central was in chemistry
那在中環就業人在化學的時候
we also do
我們也做
Many of my colleagues are also doing this kind of research.
我有很多同事也是做這類的研究
did a pretty good job too
也做得相當的好
of course
那當然
My interest is sometimes
我的興趣其實有時候
most of the time
很多時候
Not the same as others
跟人家也不太一樣
It was when my classmates were going to TSMC
就是當年我同學都要去台積電的時候
I choose to study chemistry
我就選擇念化學
so of course they are doing
所以當然他們都在做
this when i look at
這個當我看著
A lot of people do this when Invipend
Invipend的時候很多人都在做這些
solar cell what?
太陽能電池啊什麼
but i think
可是我覺得說
I don't know because maybe I'm more afraid of competition
不知道 因為可能是我比較害怕競爭
I think I might not win even in competition
我覺得說競爭我可能都不會贏人家
in this way
這樣子
or I feel tired of competing
或是我覺得競爭很累
So we just make a new one that is
所以我們就做一個新的就是
I want to know what he is biologically
我想知道他在生物體上
how do we combine
我們要怎麼樣去結合
how to design
要怎麼樣去設計
How do we make this phenomenon available in living organisms
我們怎麼樣讓這個現象可以在生物體上
Can
可以
non-stop application
不停的應用
right
對不對
So let me introduce one more
那所以我再跟大家介紹一個
the most important thing is to say
最重要就是說
just mentioned one thing
剛剛提到一件事情
Even living organisms have electricity
就是生物體也是有電
But with
可是跟
The electricity of electronic components is not the same as electricity
電子元件的電是不一樣的電
What about the electricity in living organisms?
那生物體上的電要怎麼做呢
this is the nervous system
這是神經系統
nervous system
神經系統
This is what I cut out from a paper
這個是我從一個paper上剪下來的
so more complicated
所以比較複雜
But the main thing is that there is this so-called
但是最主要的是有所謂的這個
Bandwide section
Bandwide的部分
There is a part called Axon
有所謂的Axon的部分
what is so called
那有所謂的
the most important
最重要的
I think this simplifies it
我想這個把它簡化一下
explain to you
跟各位解釋一下
the most important thing is to say
最重要的就是說
it is done by some
它是藉由一些
easy one
容易的一個
concentration difference
濃度的差別
produces a so-called
產生一個所謂的
Potential difference
電位的差別
this is called
這稱之為
Usually we call it Axon Potential
通常我們稱之為Axon Potential
kinetic potential
就是動電位
That is, it uses some of the
也就是它利用裡面的一些
ion channel
離子通道
Contains the ion channel
包含那離子通道
or pseudo ion channel
或假離子通道
when using it to send out ion channels
利用它送出離子通道的時候
The resulting potential difference
產生的電位差
between different cells
它在不同的細胞間
This potential difference can be transmitted continuously
可以不停的傳送這個電位差
and then at the end
然後到了尾端的時候
when it utilizes this so-called Excel tail-end
它利用這個所謂的Excel的尾端的時候
it utilizes this tail
它利用這個尾端
This potential can stimulate it
這個電位可以刺激它
to secrete so-called neurotransmitters
去分泌所謂的神經傳導物質
to the next neuron source
傳導到下一個神經源
So one of the most important things is
所以最重要的一個事情是
source of the signal
產生訊號的來源
In fact, these ions and these
其實這些離子跟這些的
neurotransmitter
神經傳導物質
Now here comes the problem
那現在問題來了
our electric substance
我們電的物質
The signal transmitted is from electronic and electric
傳送的訊號是來自電子跟電動
Neurogenic is derived from ionic
神經源是來自離子
What about these two things?
那這兩個東西我們怎麼
to talk
去交談
how to talk
怎麼去talk
at this time
這個時候
conductive polymer
導電高分子
another feature
另外一個特性
when we designed
當我們當初設計的時候
don't know
不知道這樣子
but
但是
It's amazing in a
它就很神奇的在一個
Such a one with a plan
有計畫物的這樣一個
Naturally, there will be such characteristics
自然的就會有這樣的特性
this is where we go now
這就是我們現在去
let's take a closer look
我們先再仔細看看
If a conductive polymer
如果一個導電高分子
It is a structure like this
它是這樣的一個結構
That might be a molecular structure like this
那在分子上可能是一個這樣的結構
when it
當它
when current is applied to it
給它電流的時候
That is, when you give it an electrical signal
也就是給它一個電信號的時候
This compound molecule
這一個化合物分子
The polymer itself will be oxidized
高分子本身會被氧化
produces an electrochemical reaction
會產生一個電化學反應
That is to say, the chemical system
也就是說化學系統
It was great
本來就是很厲害的
can combine electricity and chemistry
可以把電跟化學產生一個
medium
媒介
It produces an electrochemical reaction after
它產生一個電化學反應後
Because the entire conductor must maintain electrical neutrality
因為這整個導體必須要維持電中性
So it must start from
所以它必須從
Easy to absorb ions in
容易中把離子吸取進來
that is, naturally
也就是自然而然的
It takes this electrical signal
它就把這個電信號
becomes an ion signal
就變成了離子信號
And how much electricity do you add
而且你加多少個電
How many ions does it absorb
它就要吸多少個離子
These two will produce a linear relationship
這兩個會產生一個線性的關係
That is, conductive organic conductive materials
也就是說,導電的有機的導電材料
itself is a good way to connect electrons and ions
本身就是一個很好的把電子跟離子
A tool that can do a signal conversion
可以做一個訊號轉換的一個工具
That's why we can quickly
這也就是為什麼我們很快的就可以
Putting conductive polymers on their own can do things like
把導電高分子本身就可以做這樣的事情
And in this process, there is actually a side effect
而且在這樣過程中,其實還有一個副作用
It's because you sucked in the ions
就是因為你吸了離子過來
So this thing gets bigger
所以這東西體積會變大
If the volume becomes larger, you can feel it
那體積會變大的話呢,你就可以發覺到
it will produce if you stick it on a board
它就會產生如果你把它黏在一個板子上
As it gets bigger, the board bends
因為它體積變大,所以這個板子就會彎曲
You restore it again, and the board comes back
你再把它還原,它板子又回來
So we can design something like
所以我們可以設計成一個像
Kinetic components, Kinetic components
有動能的底敗,有動能的元件
For example, the film below
比如說像下面的這個薄膜
It is actually a fixed state
它其實一片是固定態
One piece is the dynamic state of this conductive polymer
一片是這個導電高分子的動的態
So you can tell when I give it a Pulse
所以你可以發覺到我給它一個Pulse的時候
It can produce a vibration phenomenon
它就可以產生一個振動的現象
produce such a movement phenomenon
產生一個這樣的一個運動的現象
This can be used as a
這可以作為一個,我們那時候參之為
actuator or a more popular name
actuator或是比較通俗的名字
we call it artificial muscle
我們稱之為人造肌肉
like your muscles
就像你的肌肉一樣
can move around like this
可以這樣動來動去
can move around
可以動來動去
Just call it artificial muscle
就稱之為artificial muscle
ok
ok
so i want to share
所以我想要分享一下
So such organic bioelectronic components
所以這樣的有機生物電子元件
on application
在應用上
There are many possible potential
就有很多的很可能的potential
Of course, I like this field very much.
當然我自己是非常的喜歡這個領域
I also believe that this field has considerable value in the industry
我也相信這個領域在產業上是有相當的價值
Especially in Taiwan so big
尤其在台灣這麼大
Such a powerful electronic component
這麼厲害的電子元件
With the support of an electronics factory
電子廠的一個支持下
With such good technology
有這麼好的技術的情況下
This direction is actually for the electronics factory
這個方向其實對於電子廠來講
It's not that hard to get into the horizontal ditch
並不是那麼難進去的橫溝
Maybe even sometimes I think it's better than medicine
可能甚至有時候我覺得比製藥啊
Biological technology may be even easier
生技或許還要更容易一點
because we have mastered ourselves
因為我們有掌握到本身
It is the technology of making this electronic component
就是做這個電子元件的技術
The main generation may have bio-detectors
主要的產生的可能有生物偵測器
or a bioelectrode
或者是生物電極
Or there are some so-called neurological
或者是有一些所謂的神經的
stimulating electrodes
刺激的電極
that's sorry for the rest
那不好意思剩下的東西
I don't know how to turn
我不太清楚要怎麼翻
so i use english
所以我用英文
the so-called
那所謂的
It's getting married
Ishada
so-called artificial muscles
就是所謂的人造肌肉
I just gave you an example
我剛剛有跟大家舉個例子
or so-called
或所謂的
Medical Bionics
Medical Bionics
just like that
就是像剛剛那個
like robocop
機器戰警一樣
how do i get my brain waves
我如何讓我的腦波
can control me outside
可以控制我外面的
The movement of this biomimetic system
這個仿生系統的運動
even
甚至
There are still many
目前還有很多
Includes Electronic Skin
包括Electronic Skin
is how on your skin
就是如何在你的皮膚上
started to put on
開始有裝上
Install the detector
裝上砍測器
So when your hand moves
所以當你手運動的時候
This receptor naturally has a signal
這感受器自然就有訊號
you can learn
你可以了解到
You can send signals automatically
你可以自動的傳遞訊號
even
甚至
I have new ones recently
我最近還有新的
one is someone put
一個是有人把
such a wafer
這樣的一個晶片
implanted in your nervous system
植入你的神經系統
Then use a phenomenon of biological
然後利用生物體的一個現象
when an electric signal is emitted
放出電信號的時候
The nervous system stimulates the immune system
神經系統會刺激免疫系統
Immunotherapy can begin
可以開始產生免疫療法
this you on the internet
這個你在網路上
can be found
都可以找得到
I
我
How to Harness Organic Bioelectronic Components
如何利用有機生物電子元件
as a medicine
作為一個藥
Use it to stimulate your body to release
利用它來刺激你的身體去放出
Chemicals your body is supposed to release
本來你身體就應該放出的化學物質
Diseases that cause your body can be cured
導致你身體的疾病可以得以痊癒
Some people are doing these studies
這些研究 都有的人在做
very responsible of course
都很負責 當然
I have to tell everyone here
我必須要跟大家在這邊要
Well, it's just a matter of being a member.
好 就是算是成員一件事情
actually
其實
Organic Electronic Components
有機電子元件
enough trouble
已經夠麻煩了
Because organic electronic components contain chemical
因為有機電子元件包含了化學
physics engineering
物理 工程
Well, if you think about it, organic bioelectronic components
那你想想看 有機生物電子元件
Includes Chemistry, Physics, Engineering, Biology and Medicine
包含化學 物理 工程 生物 跟醫學
So all of you have to come together
所以你全部的都要合在一起
This is totally transpsychic research
這是完完全全的跨靈異的研究
you are unlikely to do it alone
你不太可能一個人做
You have to have a lot of like minded people
你必須要有很多志同道合的人
would like to share this
願意一起來分享這個
Such research goals, research ideals
這樣的研究目標 研究理想
to be able to do
才能夠做
I'm lucky enough to always have
我以幸運的是一直都有
People are willing to cooperate with me
人願意跟我一起合作
so we
所以我們
I actually basically do stuff
我其實基本上 我做東西
see you later
等一下會跟大家見
Actually the most basic one
其實是最基本的那個
maybe say yes
可能說是
You can say it is the most critical one on the component
你可以說是元件上最關鍵的那個
But it's actually very simple
但是其實也很簡單
All I do is say how to control
我做的只是說如何去控制
this electronic component
這個電子元件
an interface with the organism
跟這個生物體的一個介面
How to make this interface ensure that
如何讓這個介面能夠確保
electrical and biological signals
電的訊號跟生物訊號
able to deliver the complete
能夠完整的傳遞
won't lose
不會失去
using chemistry and materials
利用化學跟材料的方式
this is what i'm doing
這是我在做的事情
I don't design electronics
我並不設計電子元件
I'm not going to take these either
我也不去把這些
Neither do I
我也不
Actually I also
其實我也
maybe we will
或許我們將來會
But we're not doing animal testing right now
但我們現在還沒有在做動物實驗
neither do we
我們也沒有
we also ask the doctor
我們也是請醫生
or who cooperates
或是誰合作
Let's learn about this together
一起去瞭解這方面的
possibility
可能性
OK
OK
That
那
for the rest of the time
接下來的時間
I
我
I still want
我還是要
I think
我想
still want to introduce
還是要介紹一下
what are we doing
我們自己到底在做什麼
because at least
因為最起碼
I just talked for so long
剛剛我講了這麼久
it's not what we do
都不是我們在做的
Thanks
謝謝
I just want to introduce
我只想為大家介紹一下
what we do
我們做的東西
I probably spent just a little bit of time left
我大概花的就是剩下一點點的時間
I just introduce an example
我只介紹一個例子
materials we use
我們用的材料
It is also a conductive polymer material
也是一個導電高分子材料
Its organic structure looks like this
它的有機結構是長得像這個樣子
If you want to know something today
如果你今天想要知道一件事情
I strongly recommend that you know we're doing big P
我強烈建議你知道我們在做P大就好
This material is called PEDOT for short.
這個材料簡稱叫做PEDOT
no Chinese
沒有中文
English is called PEDOT
英文就叫PEDOT
When you talk about PEDOT, everyone knows it better.
你講PEDOT其實大家比較清楚
that this material
那這一個材料
What I'm introducing to you is
我跟大家介紹的就是
of organic electronics
有機電子界的
how to say
怎麼講
if you are american
如果你是美國人的話
You say the Michael Jackson of organic electronics
你就說有機電子界的Michael Jackson
Or the Jay Chou of organic electronics
或是有機電子界的周杰倫
He's the Super Young of the Organic Electronics World
他是有機電子界的超級年輕
His patent expired last year
他的專利在去年過期
Then the whole world is making this material
然後全世界都在做這個材料
parks in taiwan
台灣的公園院
Wait for me to ask, I said how to make this material
等我來問過我說這個材料怎麼做
Because this material is a super material for organic electronics
因為這個材料是有機電子機的超級材料
its cause
它的原因
it has a chemical reason
它有化學的原因
Let me analyze it a little bit with you because I think
我跟大家稍微分析一下 因為我覺得
It is my responsibility
這是我的責任
You can see double bond single bond
大家可以看到雙鍵單鍵
This is the basic one
這個是基本的一個
The structure of conductive polymer
導電高分子的結構
But a very important issue in conducting polymers is
但是導電高分子中很重要的一個問題是
these two positions
這兩個位置
would have been empty
本來是空的
if you are empty in
如果你是空的在
When making this film, there may be
做這個薄膜的時候 有可能會產生
Accidentally connect the wrong look
不小心接錯的樣子
it is possible to get here
它有可能接到這裡
If you have a handle, please draw it
大家如果有指柄去畫一下
If this key is accidentally attached here
如果把這根鍵不小心接到這裡的話
It will not form a single bond double bond single bond double bond structure
它就不會形成單鍵 雙鍵 單鍵 雙鍵的結構
Then its conductivity will become poor.
那這樣它的導電性就會變差
the second is
第二個是
So in this molecule these two positions are completely blocked
所以在這個分子中 這兩個位置已經完完全全被阻擋住了
And the two oxygen
而且這兩個氧
will provide a function
會提供一個功能
it will make this one thing
它會讓這一個東西的
Oxidation Potential Decrease
氧化電位降低
become more suitable for
變成比較適合在
Use in normal condition
一般的狀態下使用
Do not use at too high a potential
不用在太高電位的情況下使用
so
所以
This molecule has a very ingenious structure
這個一個分子很巧妙的結構
it accomplishes many things
它完成了很多事情
it has high conductivity
它有高導電性
it has few flaws
它有很少的缺陷
and very stable
而且非常大的穩定性
because all its places are filled
因為它所有的位置都被佔滿了
impossible
沒有可能
There will be various
會有各項
And it's conductive this element
而且它的導電的這個元件
blocked in this all
被擋在這個所有的
middle of molecular structure
分子的結構中間
that first this
那最早這個
Polymer is a
高分子是一個
Bayer AG
是德國拜爾公司
Developed by Bayer AG
拜爾AG開發出來
So at first it had a
所以最早它有一個
The commercial name is called Biochrome
商業的名稱叫做Biochrome
but then
但是後來又
Everyone knows Peter
大家都知道叫Peter
then later became Helix Corporation
然後後來變成Helix公司
so it's so far
所以它在目前為止
it's in all sorts of places you
它在各式各樣地方你都
In fact, conductive polymers, we all think that they
其實導電高分子,我們大家以為他
This electronic component
這項電子元件
OLED, none of us has OLED, not everyone has an LED TV
OLED,我們每個人都沒有OLED,不是每個人都有LED電視
But some conductive polymers
但是有些東西的導電高分子
Already used in your daily life
已經在你們日常生活中已經有用到了
like solid capacitors
像固態電容
Solid capacitors are basically poly pyro
固態電容基本上全部都是poly pyro
They are all skin-determined solid capacitors
就都是具皮定的固態電容
Because his capacitance is also very good
因為他的電容度也非常好
even solid capacitors, even supercapacitors
甚至固態電容,甚至超電容
conductive polymer
都有導電高分子的中意
So this material already has very, very many possibilities
所以這個材料已經非常非常的多的可能性
It contains organic thermoelectric materials
它包含有有機的熱電材料
Organic Antistatic Materials
有機的去抗靜電材料
Contains ultracapacitor material
包含超電容材料
Even contains organic color-changing glass
甚至包含了有機的變色玻璃
Many people are doing this thermoelectric material
這個很多人都在做這個熱電材
So I say this material is the Jay Chou of the organic electronics world
所以我說這個材料是有機電子界的周杰倫
Just remember, it is Jay Chou
大家只要記得,它就是周杰倫
When I see Jay Chou, I think of him
看到周杰倫就想到他
OK, let's continue to introduce
OK,我們繼續的介紹一下
Our own laboratory, in fact, one of the characteristics of the organic
我們自己的實驗室,其實有機的一個特色是
because you have all kinds of organic structures
因為你有各式各樣的有機結構
So we can use organic synthesis
所以我們可以用有機合成的方式
To bring out the functionality of the material we want
去帶出我們要的材料的官能性
brought out in molecular design, we can control its molecular design
帶出在分子設計上,我們可以去控制它分子的設計
In nanostructures, we can use such materials
在奈米結構上,我們又可以利用這樣的材料
Can form different nanostructures
可以形成不同的奈米結構
Of course because today we're going to talk about nanostructures
當然因為今天我們要講奈米結構
So I won't introduce you to nanostructures anymore
所以我不再為大家介紹奈米結構
We can take advantage of its nanostructure
我們可以利用它的奈米結構
It's like saying we have two weapons
等於說我們有兩種武器
That is, if we put it together
也就是說我們把它結合在一起的話
We can be applied in many, many aspects of biomedicine
我們可以應用在很多很多生物醫學的方面
The pope that contains biological images is going to be done in our laboratory
我們實驗室要做的包含有生物的影像的pope
Contains biological detection
包含生物的detection
Often a speech might be either this or this
通常演講可能不是講這個就是講這個
It is biological detection
就是生物的detection
or organic bioelectronics
或者是有機的生物電子
Then I will just introduce to you today
那我今天就只為大家介紹一下
we are in our laboratory
我們在我們的實驗室中
By different molecular design
藉由不同的分子設計
we can list
我們可以歸列出
We can design two kinds of molecules
我們有可以設計出兩種分子
One is able to bring out its importance
一種是能夠帶出它的重要性
For example, there are some organic shut-off groups at the end
比如說它的尾端有一些有機的關能機團
Or you could say it's a living organism's shutdown mechanism
或者你可以說這是生物的關能機團
Because it contains succinic acid and contains amine groups
因為包含酥酸跟包含胺基
Even contains some like this Malayimid
甚至包含一些像這個Malayimid
or some sugar group
或是一些糖類的group
Even or some groups of stacked eggs
甚至或一些疊蛋的group
It can quickly combine with living organisms as a co-pilot
它都可以很快的跟生物體做一個共駕艦的結合
And produce the functionalities we need
而產生我們所需要的關能性
on the other hand
另外一方面
It has another set of monomers
它有另外一系列的單體
is used to control the properties of the surface of the material
是用來控制這個材料它表面的性質
For example, we can touch the surface
比如說我們可以在表面接觸
Pick up a lot of Foki
接上很多的佛基
Then connect with Doverki and he becomes
那接上多佛基他就變成了
Teflon like material
像鐵弗龍一樣的材料
Can
可以
Nonstick
不沾
can do many things
可以做很多的事情
can also be connected
也可以接上
For example, water-based materials
比如說清水性的材料
especially these
尤其這些
very very clear material
非常非常清水性的材料
Include
包含
Polyethylene glycol
Oligoacetylene glycol
contains some
包含一些
Dielectric materials
雙電性的材料
can let him
都可以讓他
can go
可以去
lead him to the organism's
導致他跟生物體的
Binding is very, very selective
結合是非常非常地具有選擇性的
These are actually
這些其實都是
we are imitating
我們就在模仿
Molecular Design in Organisms
生物體中的分子設計
we just put
我們只是把
put it on the main chain
把它的主鏈
replace us
換成我們
Just the conductive polymer material you want to use
想要用的導電高分子材料而已
The most important thing is that we first have
那最主要是我們先是有
More than 80 such monomers
超過80種以上這樣的單體
has been synthesized
曾經被合成過
probably also
就大概也是
Because in fact, it is probably one of the labs that have done the most
因為其實大概也是做過最多的一個實驗室之一
On the other hand, they can also be processed by a different so-called molding process
另外一方面,他們也可以藉由不同的所謂的塑裝的過程
Or the process of real science, the process of Lysography
或者是實科的過程,Lysagraphy的過程
They can make all kinds of different, different difficult materials
他們可以做出各式各樣不同的,不同的難理材料
I just want to introduce to you, we have done some
我只是為大家介紹一下,我們曾經做過包含的
All kinds of materials with thin films and materials with rice noodles
各式各樣有薄膜的材料,有耐米線的材料
Material with resistant rice grains
有耐米粒的材料
There are also hollow resistant rice grain materials
還有空心耐米粒的材料
There are even some like fibers, fibrous materials
甚至還有一些像fibers,纖維化的材料
Even the material of the rice point, even the material of the rice column
甚至耐米點的材料,甚至是耐米柱的材料
We've all done a lot, a lot of different materials
我們都做過非常非常多各式各樣的材料
Why?
為什麼?是變成這樣,要找夠
right?
對不對?
So in a situation like this
所以在這樣的情況下
We make such a wide variety of materials
我們做的這樣各式各樣的材料
Can be applied in different places
可以應用在不同的地方
can control
可以去控制
In the experiment we started with
在我們開始的實驗中
we want to control cells
我們是想要控制細胞
i.e. living organisms
也就是生物體
because it is called an organism
因為叫做生物體
It is unlikely that we will directly make chairs
我們不太可能直接做椅子
Let's start with cells
我們一開始先做細胞
Do a cell experiment in vitro
做體外做一個細胞的實驗
We can understand cells in living organisms
我們可以了解細胞在生物體上
How can the best behave
最大能夠怎麼樣的behave
ok , now back to the one thing i just said
好,那現在回到我剛剛講的一件事情
As I said, when I first started PHS
我說過,當我剛開始念PHS的時候
I really want to directly
我很想要直接把
buy one
買一個
Actually I said
其實我說
It seems that we have asked our professor
好像還有問過我們教授說
Can I buy a piece of TFT
我可不可以去買一片TFT
then cut it all
然後把它切一切
Then stuff it in that animal
然後往那個動物就塞下去
That
那
Let's see if we can record the animal's telegram.
看能不能記錄一下動物的電訊
that's
那可是
Actually this should not work
實際上這樣應該是行不通的
Why
為什麼
I will introduce you a little
我跟大家稍微介紹
This thing is called obligatory response
這個東西叫做義務反應
i believe in speaking obligatory response
我相信講義務反應
You may feel
你們或許大家會覺得
clam what is this
蛤 這什麼東西
But everyone has probably been hurt
但是每個人可能都受過傷
everyone will notice that
大家會注意到說
If you accidentally drop something
如果你不小心的把一個東西
into your hand
扎到你的手裡
how will your hands react
你的手裡會有什麼樣的反應
it doesn't bleed all the time
它不會一直流血
it won't bleed
它不會流血不止
it will find a way to heal it
它會想辦法去heal它
The way it goes to treat it is simple
它去治療它的方式很簡單
it's in your
它在你的
It only has this obligation to go in
它光有這個義務進去
It triggers a series of immune responses
它會去誘發一系列的免疫反應
Let your body automatically produce a protective function
讓你的身體自動的產生一個保護機能
This protective function means
這個保護機能就是說
wrap it up
把它包起來
create a thin membrane to wrap it around
產生一個細膜把它包起
wrap that thick film around it
把那個厚膜把它包起來
that so
那所以
You may have heard many such testimonies
或許大家也聽過很多這樣的見證
that is to say, for example
就是說譬如說什麼
during world war two
二次世界大戰的時候
There are a lot of people who take out some kind of shards of glass in their heads
有很多人在腦中取出什麼一堆玻璃碎片
They are comparable to this shard of glass
他們跟這個玻璃碎片相當
Or a bunch of these eggshells were taken out all over the body.
或是在身體上到處都取出了一堆的這個蛋殼啊
Somebody even has a bullet and stays in that
甚至有人有子彈就留在那個
Of course some are comics and some are real
有的當然有的是漫畫有的是真的
In fact, sometimes comics are written like real
其實有的時候漫畫寫的像真的
I don't know which is real and which is manga
不太清楚哪個是真的哪個是漫畫
But many such cases exist
但是很多這樣的case都是存在的
That's actually the body's natural protective response.
那其實就是人體有個自然保護的反應
when he sees something
當他看到一個東西
He thinks it's not time for amypods
他覺得這不是非我足類的時候
He is learning the Great Wall right next to him
他就在旁邊足習一個萬里長城
separate it
把它分開來
It's not just this but all objects will have a reaction
這不但是這個是所有的物體都會有一個反應
so but just thinking about it
那所以但是正想想看
Then you go in with such a thin chip
那你這樣一個細晶片進去
For him, detail is something he has never seen in his body
對他來講細是他身體中從來沒有看過的東西
There is actually no thin body in that body
那身體中其實是沒有細的
what should he do
他怎麼辦
Of course he treats it as a foreign object
他當然是把它當外物處理
So the thin wafer goes in
所以細晶片進去
He's sure to make a thick layer of it
他一定會把它產生一個厚厚的層
And then you want to see your thick biological layer
然後這樣的話你想看你這個厚厚的生物層
is an insulating layer
就是一個絕緣層
It must prevent the signal from being transmitted
它必定讓電訊號就傳不出去
So in this case
所以這樣的情況下
There is no way we can continue to use this chip
我們就沒有辦法繼續使用這個電晶片
so for this matter
所以為了這件事情
what we can do is
我們能夠做的是
We can do proper molecular design
我們可以做適當的分子設計
Find a way to turn this immune response
想辦法把這個免疫反應
or protection
或保護作用
suppress it
把它壓抑下去
That is a very common method
也就是很常見的一個方法
is the so-called use
就是所謂的利用
Bionic materials
仿生材料
we are hospitalized at central
我們在中央就院
when i was in japan
在以前在日本的時候
have also developed a series of
也都開發了一系列的
Organic Conductive Materials Imitating Cell Membranes
仿細胞膜的有機導電材料
That is to say
也就是說
look carefully
大家仔細看
Today the cell membrane is made of a pile of paper
今天細胞膜是由一堆紙質
form the cell membrane
形成這樣的細胞膜
it is clear water on one side
它一邊是清水的
one side is water
一邊是輸水的
Today if we put the water delivery end
今天我們如果把輸水端
All replaced with conductive polymer
全部的用導電高分子取代
Then keep the water list
然後保留清水單
In this way we get a material
這樣的話我們就得到一個材料
Much like a cell membrane, but it retains its clear water end
很像細胞膜,但是它保留了它的清水端
At the same time, on this conductive polymer, we can also learn how cells
同時,在這個導電高分子上,我們也可以學著細胞
to lead to some specific identification
去引導一些特定性的辨識
For example, there are various proteins on the cell membrane
比如說細胞膜上有各式各樣的運用蛋白質
Cell recognition using amino acids and even sugars
運用胺基酸,甚至運用糖類所產生的細胞辨識
We can all use molecular design to induce such cell recognition
我們都可以用分子設計的方式去誘導這樣的細胞辨識
For example, we can connect various protein leagants to conductive polymers
比如說我們可以在導電高分子上接上各式各樣的蛋白質的leagant
Some of the so-called ligands of these proteins are currently commonly used in academia
這些蛋白質的所謂的一些配體都是目前在學界常用的
So ours contains the so-called RGD, a leapt like RGD
所以我們的包含所謂的RGD,RGD這樣的一個leagant
Or the leanant like IKVAV, the leanant of RGD is cut out from the so-called collagen
或者是IKVAV這樣leagant,RGD的leagant是從所謂的膠原蛋白中切取出來的
We can control this interface
我們就可以去控制這個界面
can achieve what we want to do is
可以達到我們想要做的是
At the same time, it will not produce rejection reaction with organisms
同時它跟生物體不會產生排斥反應
What about such a design?
那這樣的一個設計呢
We did some simple experiments
我們就做了一些簡單的實驗
Although simple
雖然說簡單
But the whole experiment took about three or four years
但整個實驗也花了大概三四年
from molecular design
從分子設計
From designing one like this one
從設計一個這樣子的一個
one that can culture cells
可以培養細胞的一個
simple one
簡簡單的一個
one
一個
a so-called platform
一個所謂的平台
Then we grow cells on top of
然後我們在上面我們培養細胞
Coated with our different materials
塗上我們不同的材料
let's compare it
我們去比較它
appearance of cultured cells
培養細胞的樣子
so
所以
I can only give you a brief report on the results
我只能帶大家稍微簡短的報告一下結果
These two are compared
這兩個是對照
This is the control group
這個是對照組
These two are the experimental group
這兩個是實驗組
One of the experimental group had applied voltage
實驗組的一個有加電壓
one without voltage
一個沒有加電壓
We use our new biomimetic cell membrane conductive polymer
我們利用我們新的仿生細胞膜的導電高分子
And in the case of appropriate private family pressure
並且在適當的私家外家定壓的情況下
We achieved a very good result of stimulating the growth of nerve cells
我們達到了一個非常好的刺激神經細胞生長的一個結果
That is to say, we use the simplest way
也就是說我們用最簡單的方式
is the way we look at how fast neuron protrusions can grow
就是我們看神經細胞的突出能夠長多快的方式
let's measure
我們去測量
What we get is one of the highest values ​​ever seen on the striae
我們得到的是在紋線上由史以來最高的一個值
about two and a half times higher
大概是增高了兩倍半
That is, there is an increase in length of 1.5 times
也就是有增加了1.5倍的長度
It's just a simple application of a voltage and some molecular design
只是很簡單的加了一個電壓運用一些分子設計
I think the most important reason is because we are in such a biomimetic molecular interface
我想最重要的原因是因為我們在這樣的一個仿生的分子介面中
We make sure that the electron follows this
我們確保電子跟這個
There is a good electron ion transfer effect between cells
細胞間有一個很好的電子離子的傳遞效益
That is to say, such an electrical signal can properly enter the ions through
也就是這樣的一個電訊號能夠適當的進到離子通過
ions are generated inside
裡面產生離子訊
As for the very detailed
那至於非常細細的
Very detailed Mechanism
非常詳細的Mecanism
In fact, we have until now
其實我們到現在
We are still looking for
我們自己也還在追尋
How to do such an experiment
到底怎麼去做這樣的實驗
But in the early days of this
但是在初期的這個
in the design of a so-called platform
所謂的一個平台的設計中
We've seen very, very good results
我們看到了非常非常好的結果
Of course this thing is just us
當然這個東西只是我們
small step
很小的一步
We also did a series of
我們還有做了一系列
New things
新的東西
include us
包含我們又
So this thing is in
所以這個東西在
most importantly
最主要是
we are at
我們在
We can use this cell membrane
我們就可以利用這樣的細胞膜
for electrical stimulation
就用在電刺激
Application of so-called electrostimulatory cell engineering
所謂的電刺激細胞工程上的應用
We hope that in the future we can use it to make
我們希望將來可以用來做成
The so-called electrical spine
所謂的神經電脊
Neuroelectric spines can stimulate nerve growth
神經電脊可以刺激神經的生長
Today if there is an unfortunate patient who has the so-called
今天如果很不幸的有病人有所謂的
The so-called spinal injury
所謂的脊椎的受傷啊
or when there is an acute need
或是什麼時候有急性的需要的時候
we need to be able to help them
我們需要能夠幫助他們
Can stimulate the growth of electric cells
能夠刺激電細胞的生長
But it's still early
不過這個都還很早
Just reached the cell level
才剛做到細胞的level
Cell Hierarchy
細胞的層級
not only
不但
I give this example
我講這個例子
In fact, let everyone know
其實是讓大家知道說
Such a simple and deceptively simple result
這樣一個簡單看似簡單的結果
Contains three parts
包含了三個部分
Contains our molecular design above
包含了我們上面的分子設計
Include you want to design a
包含你要設計一個
so-called components
所謂的元件
This is of course not an electronic component
這個當然不是一個電子元件
But the simplest element
但是最簡單的元件
We have two electrodes here
我們這邊有兩個電極
Between the two electrodes there is a
兩個電極中間有一個
there is a get
有一個get
this get
這個get
cause we can add 4 plus voltage
導致我們可以加4加電壓
On a simple cell like this
在這樣的一個簡單的一個細胞上面
So we have a simple electrode design
所以我們是一個簡單的電極的設計
But you have to have elements like this
但是你必須要有這樣的元件
It stimulates the growth of cells
它能夠刺激細胞的生長
Which means you need to have a variety of people
也就是說你需要有各式各樣的人
And then finally you have to be able to analyze the results of the cells
然後最後你還要能夠分析細胞的結果
That
那
I just had a little time to introduce a
我剛最後一點時間要介紹一個
different
比較不一樣的
An idea that I researched, I would like to share with you
研究的一個idea 給大家分享一下
That is to say, our other piece
也就是說我們另外一塊
what we are doing is called
我們是在做的是所謂的
so-called smart material
所謂的智慧材料
Of course every time I talk about wisdom material
當然我每次講智慧材料
will want
都會要
In particular, we will put our own laboratory
尤其我們會把我們自己的實驗室
Organic Smart Materials Laboratory
稱之為有機智慧材料實驗室
of course there is always someone
當然總是有人
Especially some students may come to me and say
尤其是有學生可能會來問我說
Teacher, I'm not smart enough, can I come in?
那老師我不夠聰明可不可以進來
then i can only say
那我只能說
he
他
right
對不對
he is smart
他聰明嘛
he's smart
他聰明就好了
us
我們
As long as everyone works hard
就大家就很努力就好
don't need to be smart
不需要聰明
We are all about designing smart materials
我們就是要設計聰明的材料
to help our underserved humans
來幫助我們不足的人類
So what we call smart material
所以我們所謂的智慧材料
let me introduce you a little bit
我給大家稍微介紹一下
smart material that is
智慧材料也就是說
you
你
In fact, the human body
其實人體的
In the human body we have a variety of materials
人體中我們有各式各樣的材料
The material of the human body is actually a smart material
人體的材料其實本身就是一個智慧材料
for example very simple
譬如說很簡單
when you are attacked by an
你受到一個攻擊的時候
will naturally fight back
會自然的要反擊
when you get a stimulus
你受到一個刺激的時候
your body will go naturally
你人體會自然的去
elicit a series of subsequent responses
誘發一系列接下來的反應
cause the body to be protected
導致使人體的身體受到保護
no harm, right?
不會受到傷害 對不對
the human body is simple
人體很簡單
If you come alone with your fist
你如果一個人拳頭過來
you will hide
你一定會躲
you can't hide
你不可能不躲
Because this is a natural intelligent response of the human body
因為這是人體自然的一個智慧反應
So the so-called wisdom will be the same
所以所謂的智慧才會也是一樣
That is to say, when we are stimulated by an external
也就是說我們受到一個外界的刺激的時候
it will generate form
它會產生形態
or various changes
或者是各式各樣的改變
so it can respond to
所以它可以因應
It can produce a different state
它可以產生一個不同的狀態
The stimuli generated by this include a variety of
這個產生的刺激有包含很多種
There are so-called physical stimuli
有包含所謂的物理性的刺激
Contains temperature light
包含溫度 光
even magnetic fields, electric fields
甚至是磁場 電場都可能
chemical stimulation
也可以是化學的刺激
Contains pH
包含酸鹼度
Contains electrochemical reactions
包含電化學反應
Contains even your tolerance to change it
包含甚至你改變它的容忌
change it this organic this
改變它的這個有機的這個
change it to this
改變它的這個
change its volume or receptor
改變它的這個配積或者是受體
Biological words contain the simplest is
生物的話包含最簡單的就是
If your blood sugar is too high today
如果你今天血糖過高
you naturally secrete insulin
你自然就會分泌胰島素
This contains what is called a sugar stimulus
這包含所謂的一個糖的刺激
Contains even an enzyme stimulating
包含甚至是一個酵素的刺激
Of course it also contains some
當然也包含一些
Simple stimulation of a receptor and carrier
簡單的一個受體跟載體的刺激
it's all possible
這都有可能
Then we do a very simple experiment
那我們做一個很簡單的實驗
We designed another molecule
我們又另外設計了一個分子
You don't have to worry about what the molecule looks like
大家可以不用管這個分子長什麼樣
You just need to know what the molecule can do
你只需要知道這個分子能做什麼
After this molecule is oxidized
這個分子在氧化後
can make a cell or a protein
能夠讓細胞或者是一個蛋白質
Connected to this oxidized shutdown group
接在這個氧化過後的一個關能機團上面
Then whenever restore
然後每當還原的時候
The cell or the functional group will leave
細胞或者是這個關能機團就會離去
So we did a very simple experiment
所以我們做了一個很簡單的實驗
This is two sets of electrodes
這是兩組電極
If we only oxidize
我們如果只有氧化
For electrode 1, only electrode 1 will be connected to something
電極1的話,就只有1號電極上面會接上東西
Here we are very simple, we use a green dye
這邊我們很簡單,我們用一個綠色的染料
So we only oxidize electrode 1, there will be green on the electrode
所以我們只氧化電極1,就電極上會有綠色
If we oxidize electrode 1 and electrode 2, there will be green on both electrode 1 and electrode 2
我們如果氧化電極1跟電極2,電極1跟電極2上就都有綠色
If we only restore electrode 2 at this time, only the green on electrode 2 will run away
我們這時候如果只還原電極2,就只有電極2上的綠色會跑掉
That is, this is one, I just mentioned to you
也就是這是一個,我剛剛跟大家提過
An organism is a dynamic system
生物體是一個動態的系統
In other words, we now also have a dynamic system to match the dynamic system of organisms
也就是說我們現在也有一個動態的系統,去配合生物體的動態的系統
We hope this will help the organism to do something
我們希望這樣能夠幫助生物體上做一些事情
We do simple things that are actually very intuitive
我們做簡單的事情就是,其實也是非常的直覺
Let's just say that after we increase the cells through the TV
我們就說,我們藉由電視機漲完細胞後
Everyone, I have done cell experiments
大家我有做過細胞實驗
In fact, you may also know that there is a problem with the cells, the cells are very, very
其實都或許也知道細胞有個問題是細胞非常非常的
Some cells are very sticky
有的細胞非常的黏
like sticking to a surface
比如說黏在表面上
Then you want to remove the cells from this surface
那你要把細胞從這個表面
For example, today I
比如說今天我
Say it like this
比如說這樣講好了
I want to transplant this cell
我要移植這個細胞
from a thing
從一個東西
port to something else
移植到另外一個東西上
like today
比如今天
your
你的
Now there are many so-called stem cell therapeutics
現在有很多所謂的幹細胞的治療素
therapy
治療法
that is
就是說
I use your stem cells
我用你的幹細胞
After protruding a layer of cornea
伸出了一層眼角膜後
the cornea
那這個眼角膜
must
必須
After being raised outside the body
在體外養好後
must be transplanted back
必須要再移植回
on your eyes
你的眼睛上
your eyes are useful
你的眼睛才有用
but
但是
Many times on the surface of in vitro cultures
很多時候在體外的培養品的表面
it's very, very sticky
它黏得非常非常的厲害
if we don't do some
如果我們不做一些
so-called smart materials
所謂的智慧型材料的話
In that case, we can only scrape it with all our strength.
那這樣的話我們只能用滿力去刮它
Then when you scrape it with all your strength
那這樣滿力去刮它的時候
cells will be lost
細胞就會受到損失
it won't come out nicely from the surface
就不會從表面好好的出來
Does this mean that everyone has been injured?
這也就是好像大家都受過傷嘛
If it's actually a bad habit of mine
如果其實這也是我自己的一個壞習慣
When you get hurt, when you see a scar, you want to pick it
受傷的時候看到疤就會想要去摳它
It will bleed again after picking
摳完了它就會再流血
this is such a concept
這就是這樣一個概念
Today if the cells have grown
今天如果細胞已經長好了
I use Mechanical 4 to use mechanical power
我用 Mechanical 4 用機械的力量
when to dig it up
去把它挖起來的時候
its cells get hurt
它細胞會受傷
then it won't work well
那它的效果就不會好
If we use a fun
如果我們用一個很好玩的
we use a
我們用一個
Let's say we use heat-reactive stuff
比如說我們用熱反應性的東西
We just take an ice cube and put it on
我們只要拿個冰塊冰在上面
Now there are many new generation tapes that are heat reactive
現在有很多的新一代的膠帶是熱反應性的
For example, if you blow it with a hair dryer
比如說你用吹風機吹一吹
it has no glue residue
它就沒有殘膠
That is, in cases like this
也就是像這樣的情況下
We can achieve the situation of no residual glue
我們就可以達到沒有殘膠的狀況
so i want to tell you
所以我想跟大家說
We also use this situation
我們也是用這樣的狀況
We are at this time under the method of telephone learning
我們這時候在電話學的方法下
We can make this layer of cells can leave the surface
我們可以讓這層層細胞可以離開這個表面
We can detect this cell
可以我們發覺這個細胞
still alive very very well
還活得非常非常的好
OK, this last two
OK 那這個最後這兩個
Two is one of our simple
兩個是我們的一個簡單的
Share it with everyone
跟大家分享一下
Experimental results in our own laboratory
我們自己實驗室的實驗結果
Of course such an experiment
當然這樣的一個實驗
away from real commercial applications
離真正的商業的應用啊
Or the application of future technology?
或是將來科技的應用啊
still have a very long distance
都還是有非常大的一段距離
but we believe
但是我們相信
The whole thread of science should be
整個科學的脈絡應該是
we should be
我們應該是
Study science with curiosity
靠著好奇心去研究科學
what about science
然後科學呢
New Science
新的Science
Will lead to new technology
會領導出新的技術
new technology
新的技術呢
will lead new industries
會帶領新的工業
The new industry will generate a new economy
那新的工業就會產生新的經濟
Then such words
那這樣的話
This is the correct context
這樣才是一個正確的脈絡
and we don't need to say
而我們不需要說
I have to take care of myself
自己就要包餐包涵
We actually focus on the front end
我們其實專注在前端
We want to do the best science
我們想要做出最好的科學
hope this will
希望這樣就能夠
can help everyone
能夠對大家有所幫助
then i last
那我最後
make a brief summary
做個簡單的總結
uh, this is not actually a summary
呃這這其實不是總結
I conclude that I put a picture just to tell everyone that this is something that our laboratory is doing
我總結我放張圖只是告訴大家這個是我們實驗室在做的東西
Actually quite a lot
其實也是蠻多的
Then I hope that today's speech can make everyone understand the organic bioelectronic components
那我希望今天的演講能夠讓大家對有機生物電子元件這一個
I think it's a new field
我覺得是新的領域啦
But why do I think it's new?
但是為什麼我覺得是新的呢
Because sometimes I feel lonely
因為有時候覺得還蠻孤獨
because we did it for 10 years
因為我們做了10年
It seems that there are still not many people doing it
好像還是沒有很多人在做
So we think maybe when we sometimes wonder if it's
所以我們覺得可能當我們有時候懷疑說這是不是
because it's worthless
因為根本沒有價值
But I think we most want to do this 10 years
但是我覺得我們最想做這10年
We think this is a very interesting field
我們覺得這個是一個非常有趣的領域
And he and we are on this land
而且他跟我們所在的這塊土地上
I think there is a fate that is closely related
我覺得是有息息相關的命運存在
Because I think he has a very close connection with our current electronics industry
因為我覺得他跟我們現在的電子工業是有一個很緊密的連結
if there is a chance
那希望有機會的話
This is the ability to continue to the technical level
就是這個能夠繼續走到技術的層面
Even to the industrial level
甚至走到工業的層面
that is our own hope
那這是我們自己的希望
Then our specialty is material design including molecular design
那我們的專長就是包含分子設計材料設計
Hope to end up with some new apps
希望最後能夠帶給一些新的應用
and new ways to help people
以及新的一些能夠幫助人的方法
whether in biomedicine
不管是在生物醫藥上
Sometimes we also do some research on energy
我們有的時候也做一些能源方面的研究
Hope this can help you too
希望這方面也可以幫助大家
That's it, thank you all
就這樣子 謝謝大家
right now we
我們現在
Thank you Dr. You for your wonderful speech
謝謝游博士的精采演講
So we probably still have
所以我們大概現在還有
i think almost 40 minutes
我想將近40分鐘的時間
you can ask some questions
大家可以提一些問題
there is one here
這邊有一位
ask the professor
請教教授
The neurostimulation electric shock that the professor just mentioned
剛剛教授提到的神經刺激電擊
later can
以後可以
treat that
治療那個
Are you doing martial arts?
做武神經是不是
How long do you have to wait?
請問還要等多久的時間
because my newcomer has many
因為我的新人有很多
have this symptom
都有患這種症狀
Um
嗯
The question is
這個問題就是說
As for the problem of bone nerves, this is actually
做骨神經的問題,這其實
What we are doing now is actually very advanced
我們現在在做其實真的是很先端
That is, we are still making cells, we have not yet made relics
就是我們還在做細胞,我們還沒有做遺質
I haven't done the straight road yet, but what you said is the so-called bone nerve stimulation
也還沒有做直路,可是你說的所謂的做骨神經的刺激
In fact, some people have already started to use bioelectrodes to do this.
這方面其實有人已經開始拿生物電極來做了
actually
其實
me, everyone can go
我,大家可以去
maybe try to
或許可以試著去
What I just said, the so-called things like RoboCop
我剛剛講的,所謂像機器戰警那種事情
It's not impossible anymore
其實已經不是不可能的
in America , in Australia
在美國,在澳洲
There are already a lot of people who are already doing something like this
已經有很多的人已經在做這樣的事情
included in the usa
包含在美國
There are some, you can find some so-called videos on YouTube
有一些,你在YouTube上可以找到一些所謂的影片
Is someone already, for example, after he installed the legacy
是有人已經,譬如說他裝了遺資以後
He can come out with electrodes, he uses the signals from his brain
他可以電極出來,他用他腦的訊號
Directly control the walking of this foot
直接控制這個腳的行走了
He doesn't need to go through a mechanical principle
他不需要經過一個機械的一個原理
just don't need crutches
就是不需要拐杖
Instead, directly use your brain waves to control
而是直接用你的腦波去控制
Control the walking of this foot
控制這個腳的行走
on the other hand
那另外一方面
It has nothing to do with the comparison of the five nerves.
跟做五神經比較沒有關的是
In Australia
在澳洲
They do what's called an inner ear transplant
他們做所謂的內耳移植的
They use inner ear transplants
他們利用內耳移植
Such neuroelectric ridges
這樣的神經電脊
can stimulate
可以刺激
hearing recovery
聽覺的恢復
This experiment has been at least
這個實驗上已經至少
What I saw last
我上次看到的資訊
At least 30,000 people have been transplanted like this
至少已經有三萬個人以上移植的這樣
A test of a so-called electrical spine for inner ear transplantation
所謂的內耳移植的一個電脊的一個測試
So these things are already being done
所以這些東西其實已經在做
that just means
那只是說
words on the hospital side
在醫院方面的話
i have some nerves
我有跟一些神經
The surgeon has talked
外科的醫師有談過
that is
就是說
on the one hand
一方面是
Does the patient need it?
病人有沒有這個需要
can we do it
我們做不做得到
Then the doctor can't do it
然後醫生做不做得到
This is
這是
we talk all the time
我們一直都在談說
Is it possible for something like this
有沒有可能這樣的事情
Of course, it is not limited to doing ancient nerves.
當然不只限於做古神經
and many other things
還有很多其他的事情
How about that effect?
請教那個效果怎麼樣
I didn't do it when I was a kid
小時候我還沒做
have not do yet
還沒做
because they haven't done it yet
因為都還沒做
still too early
還太早
because it's still a little early
因為還有一點點早
that's it
就是這樣子
Because we're not doctors after all
因為我們畢竟不是醫生
So many times we don't
所以很多時候我們並沒有
we sometimes talk to the doctor
我們是有時候跟醫生
This is how cross-lingual cooperation looks like
跨靈運合作是這樣子
we work with doctors
我們跟醫生合作
The doctor told us about the difficulties he faced
醫生把他面對的困難告訴我們
Let's look at it from a scientist's point of view
我們看看從科學家的角度
From a technical point of view
從提供技術的角度
what can we do with them
我們有什麼能夠跟他們一起合作
So I think for patients
所以我想對於患者來講
I think the best channel of communication
我覺得最好的溝通管道
still a doctor
還是醫生
because the doctor is a bridge
因為醫生是一個橋梁
he can talk to us
他可以跟我們講
talk to patients
跟患者講
So the doctor will compare
所以說這樣的話醫生會比較
The doctor actually knows best, I think
醫生其實是最清楚我覺得
I still think the doctor knows best
我還是覺得醫生最清楚
Thanks
謝謝
ok here
好 這邊
Teacher Yu, let me ask
那個佑老師我請問一下
You just mentioned that when the power is on
你剛剛提到說通電的時候
Cells can be detached from surfaces
細胞可以從表面分離
That's the surface of dealing with that culture name
那是處理那個培養名的表面
or processing cell membranes
還是處理細胞的細胞膜
surface of the name
培養名的表面
The surface is just adding and coating or what?
表面就是加上跟coating還是怎麼樣
Yes, such a surface is the surface of our electrode
對,這樣的表面就是我們的電極的表面
Just add a coating of the conductive material we just made like this
就是加上我們剛剛那個導電材質的一個coating這樣子
So we can make it from the surface of this material
所以我們就可以讓它從這個材質的表面
make a proper disengagement
做一個適當的脫離
So you just mentioned that corner ink may be a medical material or something.
所以你剛提到是角墨可能就是醫學材料什麼那個應用
Jiaomo is another direction, but I know the direction
角墨是別的方向啦,但是我知道的方向
However, when cells are cultured
不過一般細胞在培養的時候
It was necessary to take the cells out of the cultured cotton
本來都需要把細胞從培養棉沒拿出來
to do splitting or something
來做splitting什麼的
so this kind of look you cotton
所以這種看起來你這個花棉
Should be pretty close to the application angle
應該蠻接近應用的角度
That is to say, it can be used in general cultured cells
就是說在一般培養細胞就可以用了
That's right, it can be used for general cultured cells
也沒錯,對一般培養細胞就可以用
But on the other hand, generally cultured cells
可是另外一方面是一般培養細胞就
Because what you said is right
因為你說的沒有錯啦
That is to say, it can be used, but it depends on whether the cells need it
就是說是可以用,但是就要看細胞有沒有需要
Some cells do not need
有的細胞沒有需要
Because traditional biochemical technology they, for example,
因為傳統的生化科技他們比如說
by
藉由
Add the cell membrane protein degrading enzyme Tripsin
加入細胞膜蛋白降解酶Tripsin
They use this to help it get off the surface
他們利用這個方式去幫它從表面離去
but in that case
可是那樣的話
It is said to be toxic to certain cells
就說對某些細胞會產生毒性
So really looking at the cells
所以說真的是看細胞
if the cells need it
如果細胞有需要的話
In fact, such technologies already exist.
其實這樣的Technology都有已經存在了
I believe that there are experience or people in use
我相信都有經或許人在用
The most common one is actually not the electrical stimulation we are talking about now.
最常見的其實倒不是我們現在在講的電刺激的
but thermal reactivity
而是熱反應性
We are also doing thermal reactions
我們也有在做熱反應
there is a certain type of material
就是有某一類的材質
It doesn't stick to cells when it's on ice
它在冰的時候不會黏細胞
sticky cells when hot
在熱的時候會黏細胞
This material is actually already sitting on the cornea
這個材質其實是真的已經坐在眼角膜上
Even sitting on the repair of cardiomyocytes
甚至坐在心肌細胞的修復上
research in this area
這個方面的研究
It is already being done in Japan and Europe
在日本 在歐洲已經在做了
It uses this type of
它利用這一類的
so-called smart material
所謂的智慧材料
But the heat response is exhausted and it is already being done
但是熱響應盡的已經在做了
Common cells are paired with few people who use this
一般細胞配上很少人用到這個
at least i haven't heard of it
至少我沒聽說過
yes it can
對 它可以
Because I think maybe on the one hand
因為我想可能是一方面是
Is there a need
有沒有需要
on the one hand
一方面是
Then on the one hand is the price
然後一方面是價格
hello doc
博士,你好
thank you for your excellent speech
謝謝你精采的演講
I am Jianfu
我是建復
I want to ask
我想請教一下
Just had an experiment with P.DOT
剛剛有一個實驗是P.DOT
It has a potential
它有加電位
With battery
有加電池機
One is pure P.DOT
一個是單純的P.DOT
There is another material
還有一個是其他的材質
You mentioned that it's neurological growth
你有提到說它的神經的成長
Probably can be long now
大概是目前可以長
About 2.5 times a speed
大概2.5倍的一個速度
I want to ask
我想請教一下
P.DOT is in the process of applying voltage
P.DOT它在加電壓的過程
the directionality of its current
它的電流的方向性
can be clearly located
是可以明確被定位出來的
if its directionality
如果它的方向性
can be located
是可以被定位出來的話
that neuronal outgrowth
那神經突出的成長
It is divided into S-Long and Dentrix
它有分S-Long跟Dentrix
the length of its growth
那它的這成長的長度
Is it possible to analyze the direction of his electrical stimulation?
跟他的電刺激的方向是不是可以去分析
If there is a positive correlation between them in terms of angle
如果說他們中間有角度上的一個正相關
Maybe for the future judgment on potential and its directionality
也許對於之後在電位的判斷跟他的方向性
And because we know that our creatures actually have a lot of traps on the surface
還有因為我們知道我們生物其實有很多的圈套在表面
It forms the potential area is a comprehensive effect of clustering
它形成電位區是一個群聚的綜合效應
But our biology actually tries to bring our body into balance
可是我們生物其實試著讓我們身體達到一個平衡
So its mill actually has a microcirculation magnetic field in the
所以它的磨其實有一個微循環的磁場在
Maybe this material has a magnetic field for the microcirculation of the mill
也許這個材質它對於磨的微循環的磁場
It can go to locate further things
它可以去定位出更進一步的東西
Will that affect the direction of our future nerve growth?
那會不會對我們以後的神經的生長的方向
and the direction of its stimulus
還有它的刺激的方向
Or even it pulses as often as it should
或者甚至它脈衝該有的頻率
The difference between the speed of change of its ions
它離子的變化的速度中間的差異
Implementing the diff might help
實現差異也許會有幫助呢
This question is really too professional
這個問題真的是太專業了
I say this question is very good
我說這個問題非常的好
This is the question we all ask ourselves
這問題其實我們自己都在問
That is to say, this is actually one of our current research directions.
就是說這個其實是我們現在的研究方向之一
but i want to be here
但是我想要在這邊
I always have to keep an open mind
我永遠都要保持一個很open的態度
That is to say, there is a problem with what we are doing is that
就是說我們在做的東西有一個問題是說
can we do
我們有沒有能力做
If you are interested we can always cooperate
如果你有興趣我們永遠都可以合作
In fact, our biggest problem is to say
其實我們最大的問題是說
We don't understand anything about the so-called electrophysiological
我們完全不了解所謂的電生理的
this part
這一個部分
That is to say, I will show you the result today.
也就是說我今天給大家秀這個結果
is an actually a very, very, very early result
是一個其實是一個非常非常非常早期的結果
we just do one thing
我們只是單純的做一件事
let's go see
我們去看
A chemist's point of view
一個從一個化學家的角度
Watch us change the chemical structure
看我們去改變化學結構
To simulate the structure of the cell membrane
去模擬細胞膜的結構
How would it alter the growth of the cells
會怎麼樣去改變細胞的生長
But the tiny part contains say
但是微小的部分包含說
power plant
電廠
electric current
電流
electric potential
電位
Even the micro current generated by the power plant
甚至是電廠產生的微電流
or the magnetic fields generated by power plants
或是電廠產生的磁場
is there any way to change
有沒有辦法去改
Go polar wise the growth of these cells
去polar wise這些細胞的生長
Actually we really want to do
其實我們真的很想做
But we are still working on
但是我們還在研究說
how are we going to do this experiment
我們要怎麼做這個實驗
that is how we go
也就是說我們要怎麼去
How do we design this device
我們怎麼去設計這個device
Let it produce the direction of a current we want
讓它可以產生我們想要的一個電流的方向
In fact, even we are curious
這其實連我們自己都很好奇
because what i'm going to say is
因為我要說的是
I mean it from the bottom of my heart
我說的是真的發自內心的
which means we're really, really curious
就是說我們真的非常好奇
we've always wanted to do
我們也一直想要做
But it seems that there is still a lack of knowledge
但是好像還缺乏了一點知識也
Still looking for how to do this experiment
還在尋找說怎麼樣做這個實驗
right
對
Thank you very much
很感謝你
I hope more people can benefit from this
希望之後有更多人可以受惠這樣子
we would love to do
我們是很希望做
because this also goes on to what's called cellular physiology
因為這也接著到所謂的細胞生理學
or cell electronics
或者是細胞電學
Then we need or need more people
那我們需要還是需要更多的人
let us know tell us teach
給我們知道跟我們教導說
roughly how to do this kind of experiment
大概要怎麼樣做這類的實驗
We are now simply using
我們現在只是單純的用
The simplest way is to look at how a cell needs to be done from a chemical point of view.
最簡單的從一個化學角度去看一個細胞時間要怎麼做而已
Thanks
謝謝
right
對
Does he have
下面他有沒有
ok, there is
好,這邊有
Yes, because it happens to be
對,因為剛好就是
I'm Dr. You's college classmate
我是游博士的大學同學
He just said that all college students have joined TSMC
他剛剛說全部的大學同學都進了台積電
That Fengqiao is the only one present today
那鳳橋今天只有我一個人在場
I just happened to be the one who didn't get into TSMC
我剛好是沒進台積電的那一個
So when he said that just now, he still felt hot on his face.
所以剛剛他這樣講的時候臉上還覺得滿熱的
as if talking about my feelings
好像在講我的感覺
like this
是這樣子
Because that said there is still a major problem
因為就是說還是有一個重大的問題
Like the teacher’s first question just now, how can this thing be done?
像剛剛老師的第一個問題就是說這個東西怎麼能夠做得到
because I've actually been posting the door for a while
因為我其實我在公布門一段時間
Then we are probably more in the industry
那我們大概比較在業界
As far as the most feared issue is to say
就最害怕的這種議題就是說
you may do well in the lab
你可能在實驗室內做得很好
when he started to enter Pirom
當他開始進入Pirom的時候
The trader will tell you that he can't do it
業者就跟你講說他做不出來
Or when this thing is made
或者說這個東西做出來的時候
He's going to give it to a patient.
他要給一個病人用的算是添醬
The patient basically
那這個病人基本上
Unless your thing is a very clear health insurance payment
除非你這個東西是很明確的健保給付
But we know we've heard that health insurance is about to break
但我們知道聽過健保都快要破
bankrupted
破產了
It's very likely
這可能性相當的高
So the first question is to say
所以第一個問題就是說
this thing
這個東西
probably first thing
可能第一件事情
because basically
因為基本上是
What Dr. Post is doing in his lab now
郵博士現在實驗室正在做的東西
You have been doing it for ten years
你做了十年嘛
So the first of your industry's
所以第一個你的產業的
who this corporator might be
這corporator可能是誰
Under what circumstances are you prepared to count the turn
準備在什麼情況下計轉
And you start getting closer to maturity
而且你開始越接近成熟的時候
You'll be thinking about mass production versus actual
你將會考慮到量產跟實際上
The question of the cost of being able to do this
能夠做出來的這個成本的問題
because I feel
因為我覺得
What Dr. Post just mentioned
郵博士剛剛提的東西
Obviously not just in Science
顯然不是只是在Science
or what Pay
或什麼Pay
Send a Paper on Science Network
Science Network上面發個Paper
the point is to say
重點是說
When can he really form an industry
他什麼時候可以真的形成產業
He can really use it in
他真的可以在運用在
on people who need it
需要用的人身上
So what you just said
所以你剛剛講的這個
doctor's part
醫生的部分
I feel like jumping a little faster
我覺得稍微跳得快一點
The first thing to get lucky is
要過巧的第一件事情是
Who can mass-produce this thing
誰能夠把這個東西量產出來
So your skill amount is
所以你的技能量是
who will do it first
誰先做這件事情的時候
I think this is probably the most important
我覺得這可能是最重要的
Because of this consideration
因為這個點考慮
just a little less
就比較少一點
How do you industrialize these
你怎麼把這些產業化
what is your idea
你的構想是什麼呢
ok
ok
this
這個
I think
我想
classmate
同學
no no no i just
沒有沒有沒有我只是
just say hello
先打個招呼而已
I think this part is actually
我想這個部分是其實
In fact, my personal energy is actually quite complicated.
其實我個人的精力其實也滿複雜的
I think Zhou Fu just introduced some
我想剛剛周傅介紹了一些不過
If I introduce myself, I actually
我自己介紹的話我其實
Like what they said about me returning home
像他們說我什麼回國
I feel like a wandering professor
我覺得好像流浪教授一樣
Because the highest record of this
因為最高紀錄這個
During my eight years with my wife
我跟我太太的八年內
changed four countries
換了四個國家
and moved seven times
然後搬了七次家
sister will move
妹妹會搬家
Then I actually know how to set up the laboratory
然後我其實我很會set up實驗室
Because I often move labs
因為我常常搬實驗室
so off topic
所以是題外話
In fact, when I just graduated from PhD
其實在我PhD剛畢業的時候
I have had conflicts
我有矛盾過
I have thought about what I want to do in the future
我有想過說我將來的未來要做什麼
So actually I also have
所以其實我也有
I have talked to VC
我有跟VC談過
I also talked to the industry
我也有跟業界談過
I actually
我其實也
interviewed the industry
interview過業界
I also interviewed G Plastic
我也interview過G Plastic
I even interviewed McKenzie
我甚至還有interview過McKenzie
McKenzie Consulting Firm
McKenzie Consulting Firm
So actually I probably
所以其實我大概
I probably understand what you're talking about
我大概了解你在說什麼
In fact, it's all very specialized.
其實這都是很專門的事情
The point is you have to find
關鍵是你要找到
For me I think the key is you find the right person to help you
對我而言我覺得關鍵是你要找到對的人幫你
You need to find the right partner to help you
你要找到對的partner幫你
because no one person can do everything
因為沒有一個人可以做所有的事
I have no choice now
我現在我沒有辦法
answer this question positively
正面的回答這個問題
I don't have a partner to help me now
我現在沒有partner在幫我
The second is that I don't have any
第二個是說我現在也沒有
Our thing is actually for me
我們這個東西其實對我而言
I think the biggest problem is
我覺得最大一個問題是
The first question just asked is very good
剛剛第一位問的問題非常好
which problem we can solve
就是哪一個問題我們可以解決
Because what I'm offering now is a platform
因為我現在提供的是一個平台
Platforms have the potential to solve many problems
平台是有可能解決很多問題
but to put it bluntly
但是講難聽一點
you didn't solve any problems
你並沒有解決任何問題
For example, the first question
比如說最早的一個問題
Another example, since organic bioelectronics is an emerging field
另外一個例子,因為有機生物電子是一個新興的領域
So I don't know, organic electronics in the organic electronics industry
所以不知道,有機電子在有機電子產業上
All of your animations have gone through
所有的你所有的動畫都已經經歷過了
Because of organic electronics, organic electronics just means that organic matter can emit light and generate electricity
因為有機電子,有機電子只是說有機物可以發光發電
Conducts electricity, but how does it become a product?
導電,但是它怎麼變成產品?
I don't know, so the first product is called OLED
不知道,所以第一個產品叫OLED
The second product is called OTFT, but OTFT is dead
第二個產品叫OTFT,但OTFT已經死了
OTFT has been beaten to death by GRAPHIN
OTFT已經被GRAPHIN打死了
was beaten to death by Deputy Zhou
被周副打死了
Then OLED, the second is OLED
然後OLED,第二個是OLED
Next up now is OPV
接下來現在是OPV
this is what everyone is doing
這都是大家在做的
But in the industry, in fact, sometimes we talk to business people
但是在業界,在其實在我們有的時候跟商業界人談
The business world actually cares just to say
商業界其實care的只是說
In fact, to put it simply, it is a popular saying in the past.
它其實,套句話說就是我們以前流行的句話就是
black cat, white cat, whatever your cat is
黑貓、白貓,不管你怎麼樣的貓
A cat that catches mice is a good cat
抓到老鼠的貓就是好貓
TV is TV
電視其實就電視
From a
從一個
from the customer's point of view
顧客的角度來講
He doesn't care at all it's an OLED TV
他根本不care這是OLED電視
This is an LCD TV
這是LCD電視
This is CRD TV
這是CRD電視
what he wants is this thing
他要的是這個東西的
Performance
表現
So what we have to know now is
所以我們現在必須要知道的是
identify where is the problem
identify哪裡有問題
For example, heavy femoral nerve is a problem
比如說重股神經是一個問題
This platform can solve
這個平台可以解決
Then this part we have to go through the doctor
那這個部分我們要透過醫生
Because only a doctor can tell us
因為只有醫生可以告訴我們說
this problem
這個問題
Is it possible for our platform to solve
我們的平台有沒有可能解決
So the first step I think we still have to cooperate with the doctor
所以第一步我覺得我們還是得跟醫生合作
academically
在學術上
Because academically you have not solved
因為學術上你沒有解決
Before determining what problems you can solve
確定你能夠解決什麼問題前
Let's talk about mass production first
先來談量產的話
the first is
第一個是
no one will
不會有人
Talk to you about mass production
跟你談量產
because you can't go without him
因為你沒有他沒有辦法去
Predict where your market is
預測你的market在哪裡
where is your market
你的市場在哪裡
The second question is
第二個問題是
he is not willing
他也不願意
risk him
要有他的風險
In this respect, I believe
那在這個方面的話我相信
I'm sorry I talked a little bit more
在不好意思我講的多了一點
Because I actually have quite a lot of experience
因為我其實有蠻多的經驗
that is to say in the United States
就是說在美國的話
They use the so-called SBIR System
他們是用所謂的SBIR的System
Lets you teach yourself how to start a company
讓你教授自己去成立公司的方式
go after your dreams
去追求你的夢想
So this is actually for me
所以這個是其實對我而言
I think it's a good
我覺得這是一個很好
So Taiwan also has the SBIR System
所以台灣也有SBIR的System
So instead of such a
所以相反的這樣的一個
that is
就是
SBIR is a small company that invites professors
SBIR就是小公司有請教授
put his help to this small company
把他的幫助這個小公司
Just cooperate with his students to do a simple calculation
就配合他的學生做一個簡單的計轉
That actually still uses Science
那實際上還是用Science
Or a way for Technology to Push
或是Technology來Push的一個方式
In fact, there are different models of development companies
這樣的其實有不同的開發公司的模式
I don't think it's too early to go now
我覺得大概現在不用那麼早的去
identify partner
identify partner
but i think
但是我覺得
Our biggest problem right now is
我們現在最大問題是
identify where is the question
identify where is the question
is where is the question
就是where is the question
If so, we can use this platform
如果有我們可以這個平台
Questions that can help
可以幫助解決的question
We are actually cooperating with many hospitals now
我們其實現在跟很多醫院在合作
go in a different direction
去走不同的方向
But I'm sorry we're not doing stock gods
但是很抱歉我們沒有在做股神
but we do something else
但是我們有做一些別的事情
Because I didn't talk about our other topic today
因為今天我沒有講我們另外一個題目
In fact, I am very passionate about this topic.
其實我對這個題目是非常有passion的
But we have some other research topics that are
但是我們有一些其他的研究題目是
I was talking to the hospital, I actually got into it
有在跟醫院其實有進到
Nearly doing a stage of Proven Solving
將近在做Proven Solving的一個stage
But we are not doing Proven Solving now
但是我們現在沒有在做Proven Solving
On this platform, we are just doing a pure academic discussion
這個平台上我們只是在做單純的一個學術的探討
I don't think we have reached the stage of Proven Solving now
我並不覺得我們現在已經進到Proven Solving的階段
but we are
但是我們正在
right
對
so i'm here i can't tell you
所以我在這個我沒有辦法告訴你說
which one are we now
我們現在在哪一個
There's no way to tell you how we're going to have one
還沒有辦法告訴你說我們要怎麼有一個
It's a business plan
算是一個商業上的一個plan
a business plan
一個business plan
just don't know where the problem is
就是問題在哪裡不知道
I think the question is very important
我覺得問題是很重要的
you need to know where your problem is
你要知道你的問題在哪裡
Let me ask you this
這個我請問一下
This New Rain will Out-Growth
這個New Rain會Out-Growth
president so much
會長這麼多
Then he obviously has the expression of stimulating a certain gene.
那他顯然有刺激某個基因的表現
So have you researched the expression of those genes?
所以那些基因的表示你們有研究嗎?
The reason I say this now is because
我現在講這個的原因是因為
Because you are all talking about medicine now
因為你們現在都講醫學
In fact, Taiwan's biotechnology is still in the medical field
事實上台灣的生物科技還在醫學
because my face
因為我法規面
Taiwan's laws and regulations are considered a bit too strict in the world
台灣的法規是全世界算有點過度嚴格的國家
so sometimes it can be a bit difficult
所以有時候這方面會有點困難
But some biotechnology is not necessarily directly related to medicine
但是某些生物科技不一定是直接跟醫學有關係的話
In fact, it might be faster to walk.
事實上說不定走起來會比較快一點
Like this, if you use electrodes to stimulate cells
像這種如果說用電極刺激細胞
you talk about nerves now
你現在講神經
But say something about the cells
不過說一些細胞的話
Because now Taiwan uses cells to produce protein
因為現在台灣用細胞來生產蛋白質
For example, the production of vaccines
譬如說生產疫苗
or produce some therapeutic proteins
或者生產一些治療用的蛋白
or therapeutic antibodies
或者治療抗體的話
In fact, the demand is quite high
事實上需求量是蠻高的
If your electrode stimulation can promote the expression of certain genes
如果說你電極刺激能夠促進某些基因的表現
Software can make the protein of a certain feature
Software可以讓某一個特性的 protein
Or genetically engineered proteins can be produced in large quantities
或者基因工程的蛋白可以大量產生
I look back now to say
我現在回過頭來看是說
Because what you see now is Alkose of cells
因為你現在看到是細胞的 Alkose
A bunch behind Alkose
那Alkose後面一堆
There must be a large number of expression of genes
一定有基因的大量表現
If the performance can be stimulated by this electric shock
那表現如果能夠用這電擊來刺激的話
Maybe it's another way
說不定也是另外一條路
It doesn't have to be superficial
不一定是走表面的這個
this and that
這個那個
very considerate
非常貼心
I know
我知道
thank you very much for this
非常謝謝你這個
This is actually a question I just answered
這其實就是我剛回答一個問題
we need to know
我們需要知道
where are the possibilities
where are the possibilities
This actually gives us a very good suggestion that
這個其實給我們一個很好的建議就是說
it may be a possibility
這可能是一個 possibility
then i
那我
i'm sorry
我不好意思
I didn't make this truth very clear.
這張實話我其實沒有講得特別清楚
on this side
在這一邊
rightmost image
最右邊的圖
In fact, in addition to stimulating cell growth, our TV sets
其實我們電視機除了刺激細胞生長外
because at that time hair
因為那時候發
To be honest it was because at that time
講實話是因為那時候
When you want to submit a question here
要投這邊問文的時候
that
那個
Censor says you can't just demo water your TV cell growth
審查員說你不能只demo水你的電視機細胞生長
You want demo water the second thing
你要demo水第二件事情
So without demo water the second thing is
所以沒有demo水第二件事情就是
It electrically stimulates protein secretion
它會電刺激蛋白質分泌
This protein is actually New on Gross Factor
這個蛋白質其實是New on Gross Factor
it is at
它在
Everyone I have studied New on Gross Factor
大家我有studied New on Gross Factor
New on Gross Factor
New on Gross Factor
The general New Long Long also has something called Shuang Cell
一般的New Long Long還有一種東西叫做Shuang Cell
It is used to protect the cells of New Long
它是用來保護New Long的細胞
It itself secretes New Long Gloss Factor
它本身會分泌New Long Gloss Factor
Will help the New Long inside grow
會幫助裡面的New Long生長
when we discovered the world of television
我們發覺電視界的時候
Not only does it stimulate the growth of cells inside
不但會刺激裡面的細胞生長
It also irritates the outer protective membrane
它也會刺激外面保護膜
To secrete more New Long Gloss Factor
去分泌更多的New Long Gloss Factor
I believe
我相信
you are right
你講的沒錯
what is the first DNA
第一個是什麼DNA
Actually more basic
其實更基本的
we are doing now
我們現在也有在做
What exactly is Pathway
到底是什麼Pathway
Which Pathway is it?
到底是哪一個Pathway
Because of
是因為
Adhesion Induced Pathway
Adhesion Induced Pathway
Or does it have another Pathway
還是它有另外的Pathway
we just did
我們只做了
We just did a little bit of proof
我們只做了一點點小小證明
we did an experiment
我們做了一個實驗
we prove that
我們證明說
It has nothing to do with Adhesion
它跟Adhesion一點關係都沒有
because when we use a drug
因為當我們用一個藥
When living in the Adhesion Receptor Pathway Block
把Adhesion Receptor Pathway Block 住的時候
TV still stimulates cell growth
電視機還是會刺激細胞生長
So the Machining of the TV
所以電視機的Machining
Growth-stimulating Machining
刺激生長的Machining
Pathway's Adhesion has nothing to do with it
Pathway的Adhesion是一點關係都沒有
We have done this experiment
這個實驗我們有做
because we didn't show it here
因為我們沒有在這邊秀出來
But we have done this experiment
但是我們有做這個實驗
so i want your suggestion
所以我想你的建議
It's really precious, it's really nice
真的是非常的寶貴 真的是太好了
I do
我這樣
If there is an actual
如果說有實際的一個
direction what we can do
direction我們可以去做的話
we can also discuss
我們也可以來討論一下
because I've always felt that
因為我就一直覺得說
That's right, just say
沒錯啦 就說
It's like I just re-emphasized to you
就好像我剛剛跟各位再次強調
this is a platform
這個是一個平台
We have many possibilities
我們有很多的possibility
In fact, I should think
其實應該我覺得
Because I told you this experiment arranged your experiment
因為我講你這個實驗排了你的實驗
So you should be worth analyzing that transcript
所以你應該值得去分析那個transcript
is all transcription
就是所有transcription
It can be produced under the tube type
它做系管型下可以生產
can you find it out
可以找出來嘛
So which specific genes are overexpressed?
那看哪些特定的基因表現特別多
With and without batteries
有電池機跟沒有電池機的時候
you can compare
你可以去做比較
If you compare, you will know which type of promoter
那比較的話你就知道哪類型的promoter
may be particularly stimulated
可能受到特別大的刺激
So that place is a
所以那個地方就是一個
specific research pathway
特定的研究途徑
Thanks
謝謝
today
今天
i didn't hear very clearly
我沒聽太清楚
My guess is you tried Top Down
我的猜想你試試用了Top Down
do bionics again
再做仿生
Do Modern Design again
再做Modernal Design
Top Down
Top Down
is you now identify the problem
就是你現在identify the problem
Then analyze the mechanism inside
再去分析裡面的機制
The basic elements inside
裡面的basic elements
Now many are button up
現在很多都是button up
button up can't go far
button up其實走不遠
Especially if you want to do Bio-Memetic
尤其你要做Bio-Memetic
May have to do Top Down
可能都要做Top Down
ok
ok
Thanks
謝謝
actually for me
其實對我而言
I am not very sure
我不太清楚
sorry
對不起
For me, Top Down and bottom up are Nano Science
對我而言Top Down跟button up就是Nano Science
For me those two words are Nano Science
對我而言那兩個字是Nano Science
we are using
我們在用的
but it doesn't matter
不過沒有關係
I probably know what you mean
我大概知道你的意思
i want to be in bio
我想在生物
I think it's also possible that everyone knows
我想這也可能是大家知道
everyone may do too
大家可能也做
There are many ancestors who are living creatures who know that
在場有很多做生物的先輩都知道說
The biggest problem with being a creature is that you have to identify the waste problem
做生物最大問題就是你要去identify waste的problem
So all I can say is we have the system now
那我只能說我們現在有這個系統了
Then our system we Demonstrate a problem that is
那我們系統我們Demonstrate一個problem就是說
In fact, electromechanical cell growth
其實電次機細胞生長
how to make it faster
怎麼樣讓它變得更快
this we did now
這個我們現在做到了
Then we can do it by changing the molecular structure
那我們利用改變分子結構的方式可以做到
that if
那如果
Do you think this is called top down
你覺得這個叫top down
Then I think it is top down
那我就覺得它就是top down
Because I'm actually not sure if this is called top down
因為我其實不太確定這個叫不叫top down
but it does
但是的確
Toggy or question is whether there is a problem
Toggy or問題就是說有沒有有問題的
Then how do we solve it
然後我們怎麼樣去解決的話
i think this is
我想這個是
what we do all the time
我們一直都在做的
hope to be able to do
希望能夠做
The button up of Top down is on that
Top down的button up在那個
Nanotechnology
Nano technology
is a very ordinary management
是一個很普通的管理
Yeah
對對對
It's top down, it's resography
就是top down就是resography嘛
button up is self assembly
button up就是self assembly
For us, top down is resography
對我們來講就是top down就是resography
then my simplest
那我最簡單的
i will sit on the plane
我會坐在飛機
I will divide it on the top down
我top down上面先分一下
Molecule atoms made later
做的後來做的分子原子
Button up is done from the molecular atom to the top
button up從分子原子往上面做
OK
OK
OK, is there any more?
好 那還有沒有
well behind
好 在後面
Hello doctor, I am a college student in the Department of Biotechnology
那個 博士你好 我是生物科技學系的大學生
That may not work, the problem may not be so professional theory
那個可能沒辦法 問題可能沒有那麼專業的理論
Yes, then what I want to ask is because your experiment is about electrical stimulation of cells
對 然後我想請教的是 因為你的實驗就是關於電刺激細胞這個研究
The Xianbai just now also mentioned that because it stimulates cell growth
剛剛那位賢拜也有提到說 因為刺激細胞生長
We know that there may be many proteins in the cell
我們知道細胞裡面可能很多蛋白質
So can we just focus on certain proteins
那我們能不能就是只專注在某些蛋白質
or destimulate on certain transfer factors
或者是在某些轉入因子上去刺激
Or send out some message for the receptors to pick up
或者是發出一些訊息 讓受體能夠接收到
thereby deactivating those proteases and the like
藉此去活化那些蛋白酶之類的
Yes, maybe, not the whole cell
對 就是可能 不是針對整個細胞
Maybe it's part of the genes or something like the uprightness of the cells
也許是部分的基因 或者是像是細胞的端立
It can be stimulated without shortening too quickly
可以去刺激它 不會縮短的太快
or
或者是
to enable the cell to prolong its lifespan and things like that
讓細胞能夠延長它的壽命之類的
That is, the possible research directions are more professional and more
就是可能研究的方向比較專業比較
The range is a bit smaller, but not that big
範圍比較小一點就是沒有那麼大
Just let the cells grow
單純讓細胞生長而已
Is it possible to do research on this
就有沒有可能做這方面的研究
That question is actually very good
那這個問題其實非常的好
Don't worry
不用擔心
because we are here
因為我們就是來
Just to share with you our experiments
就是跟大家分享我們的實驗
what you just said
那你剛剛講的
absolutely right
絕對沒錯
because in fact
因為其實
The simplest matter of light cell growth
最單純的光細胞生長這件事情
actually a
其實就是一個
in biomedicine
在生物醫學上
actually a very important thing
其實很重要的一件事情
Because actually I
因為其實我
Although protein analysis
雖然做蛋白質分析啊
do genetic analysis
做基因分析啊
It is very important in education
在學歷上是非常非常的重要
It is also very, very necessary to understand
也非常非常的需要去了解
Because knowing why is not just because
因為了解原因不但只是因為說
It's Santific fun
它是Santific有趣
but because
而是因為
Even if you go into that
就算你進到那個
FDA
FDA的
Even at the legal level
就算進到法規的層次的話
he needs you to know too
他也需要你知道說
What is the mechanism behind any drug or device
任何一個藥品或一個device背後的mechanism是什麼
This is the pharmacological mechanism must be known
這是藥理機制都必須要知道的
so it's all important
所以都很重要
But I think one of the things we do is
但是我想我們做的一個事情就是
What we often do is say
我們常常做的事情就是說
we also want to say see
我們也希望說看看
electrical stimulation
電刺激
Surface-bound receptor stimulation
結合表面的受體刺激
Stimulation even combined with nanostructures
甚至結合奈米結構的刺激
Can we use the fastest way
我們能不能夠用最快速的方式
to enhance cell growth
去增進細胞生長
This is actually very important in biomedicine
這其實在生醫學中是非常重要的
Of course, the reason I say this is because
當然我講這個事情的原因是因為說
Actually it has a market over there
其實它是有一個市場在那邊
Not only in research, you are very happy to save people
不但研究上你救人是很快樂的一件事情
And it does have a market over there
而且它的確是一個有市場在那邊
In fact, what many people in this market are doing is
這個市場其實很多的人在做的就是
Includes sports medicine
包含運動醫學方面
Sports medicine
Sports medicine方面
how do you make a person
你如何讓一個人
today i thought i would give a
今天我想我舉個
Because today is the enjoyment of knowledge, I will lift it up
因為今天是知識享用我都舉
relatively simple
比較通俗而已
For example, now the NBA final
比如說現在NBA final
Everyone knows that the NBA is playing the finals now
大家都知道現在NBA在打決賽
If today is unlucky
那今天如果很不幸的
Lobrom James
Lobrom James
broken foot
腳斷了
If you can get him back in a week
你如果在一個禮拜內能夠讓他復原
can he get you back
他又能不能復你
1 million US dollars
100萬美金
he must be willing
他一定願意
but you have to be good
但是你要有本事
that is how we are
就是說我們如何在
biologically listen to you
生物體上再聽你說
If we use these stimuli appropriately
如果我們利用適當的運用這些刺激
to stimulate cell growth
去刺激細胞的生長
absolutely very important
絕對是非常重要的
so i believe
所以我相信
what i said to you is not wrong
我像你講的是沒有錯的
we have done
我們有做過
we noticed
我們發覺到
Electrical stimulation coupled with stimulation of surface structures
電刺激配合表面結構的刺激
Both have additive effects
兩個是有加成的效果
Can make cells grow faster
可以讓細胞長得更快
Include
包含
so-called copying
所謂的複製
That is, the speed of proliferation will become faster
就是proliferation的速度會變快
But the proliferation is over
但是proliferation完了
You have to make sure the cells are all good
你必須要確定這些細胞長出來都是好的
Then we have to do another experiment on this part.
那這個部分我們必須要另外再做實驗
but i think
但是我想
this thing means
這東西就是說
biomedical aspects
生物醫學方面
bioelectronics
生物電子方面
organic bioelectronics
有機生物電子方面最
The hardest thing is because you have to integrate
最困難的事情是因為你必須要整合
From Upstream to Downstream Upstream Material Design
從上游到下游 上游的材料設計
Midstream Engineering Design
中游的工程設計
and then to downstream medical applications
然後到下游的醫學的應用
It all comes together so
這全部都會整合在一起 所以
sometimes we look like we
有的時候我們看起來我們
We are a little more scattered now, we don’t have folks talking about which parts are done very carefully
我們現在比較分散一點 我們沒有Folk在說哪一個部分都做得很仔細
We hope to put such a situation first
我們是希望先把這樣的一個狀況先
were able
能夠
Explain to everyone, you can do a simple Demonstration
解釋給大家聽 能夠做一個簡單的Demonstration
in this way
這樣子
there are still problems
還有問題
that because i do
那個因為我是做
IC packet analysis, so we all know
IC包分析方面的 所以我們都知道
IC package is because in terms of transfer or transfer
IC包是因為在就是轉入或轉易的方面
may have gone wrong and produced
可能出了錯誤 而產生
are bad cells, or tumors as they're commonly known.
就是不好的細胞 或者是俗稱的腫瘤
Is it possible to use electrodes to stimulate and make it
那有沒有可能用電極去刺激之後 可以讓它
wrong turn into right
錯誤的轉入轉易變成正確的
Then proceed to produce normal cells
然後進行生產出正常的細胞
can then replace the original abnormal cells
然後可以取代原本的不正常的細胞
this...
這個...
No, I think the idea is very creative
沒有,我覺得這個想法是很有創意
but i really...
但是我真的...
Sorry, I can't answer because I'm not a doctor
不好意思,我沒辦法回答,因為我不是醫生
Perhaps some doctors have done such an experiment
或許有的醫生已經做過這樣的實驗
He will tell you if this is possible
他比較會告訴你說這個有沒有可能
Because sometimes I won't tell you right away that it's not possible
因為其實有時候我不會馬上跟你講說這個沒有可能
because actually many things
因為實際上很多東西
because sometimes there are things that just don't have the right material to do it
因為有些時候有些東西是沒有適當的材料去做
The problem we often find when we make materials is
我們做材料的很多時候發現的問題是
Some people have some wrong ideas before because there was no proper material before
有些東西以前的人有一些錯誤的觀念是因為以前沒有適當的材料
Now that there are appropriate materials, is it possible to do such a thing?
那現在有適當的材料是不是可以做到這樣的事
Maybe you can try again
或許可以重新的去再測試一下
But so far we haven't been doing this.
不過目前一直這一塊我們是沒有在做
We've never heard a doctor tell us that there's such a possibility.
我們也沒有聽過醫生跟我們提過說有這樣的可能
But I guess it's an idea
不過我想這是一個想法
You can try to find literature
你可以試著去找文獻
see if anyone does
看看有沒有人做
If you find warmth and are interested
如果你找得到溫馨有興趣
Our middle school has its own program, including a PhD program
我們中院有屬其身的program 有PhD program
There are all kinds of programs, we welcome you to come
有各式各樣的program 我們都歡迎你來
thank you doctor
謝謝博士
Do you have other people's questions?
要不要有其他的人問題
I want to ask you a question
我想請教你一個問題就是
I see you've done a great job on the side of NPT
我看到你在神經創導電位之面做得非常的棒
Then you also answered some key questions about creating potential changes
然後你也回答了一些很關鍵的創導電位變化的問題
But I think whether it's in our biological or medical part
可是我想不管是在我們生物或醫學部分的話
In fact, everyone is more familiar
其實大家比較耳熟
I think it is useful for living things
我想是對於生物產生功用
is the increase or decrease in the expression of its protein
是它的蛋白質的表現量的增減
I think that's probably why when you submit
我想這可能也是為什麼你投稿的時候
will be subject to some responses
會受到一些responses的原因
So my question is
所以我想問的問題是
Parts for these BioSensor
針對這些BioSensor的部分
How to use electrical signal to detect in...
怎麼樣用電訊號去偵測在...
any target, such as a limited change in a protein in a nerve cell
有任何的目標,比如說在神經細胞內的蛋白質的限量變化
Is there such a way?
有沒有這樣的方式?
i think this question
我想這個問題
In fact, my questions today are very good, I like it very much
其實我今天問題都非常的好,我非常喜歡
Actually what you mentioned is that I just mentioned
其實你提到的是,我剛剛提到
I just gave you a simple hint
我剛剛有稍微的給你們一個簡單的一個hint
That is to say, the guide polymer
就是說,導用高分子
The guide polymer itself has a very good function, which is
導用高分子本身有一個很好的一個功能就是
Excuse me
不好意思
OK
OK
One of the biggest functions of guiding polymers is to use them as biological detectors
導用高分子一個最大的功能就是拿來做生物偵測器
Why can he be a biodetector? Because it's simple
為什麼他可以做生物偵測器?因為很簡單
You just saw that we can do molecular modification, right?
你剛剛看到我們可以做分子修飾對不對
I'm sorry, let me run another one to try love
對不起,再讓我多跑一張試愛
you can do molecular modification
你可以做分子修飾
After molecular modification
分子修飾以後呢
I can easily pick some on it
我可以在上面很簡單的接一些
Next up is Leaghan
接一些就是Leaghan
Get something to detect
接一些可以去偵測的東西
Then the conduction below you is an electrical signal
那你下面這個導電是電訊號
with a Leaghan on it
上面有一個Leaghan
So when any organism comes
所以當任何的一個生物體來
When creating a Binding with this Leaghan
跟這個Leaghan產生Binding的時候
It may affect the transmission of electrical signals below
它有可能會影響下面電訊號的傳輸
you create a difference in electrical signal
你就產生一個電訊號的差異
This electrical signal can then be used as a biometric sensor
這個電訊號就可以拿來做生物偵測器
So we're doing something like this
所以我們有在做這樣的事情
just because of today's time
只是因為今天時間的關係
I probably can't tell you all the results of 10 years
我大概沒有辦法把10年的結果都告訴你們
I only gave two examples
我只舉了兩個例子
But you said biometric sensors are really important
但是你講生物偵測器的確是很重要的
And that's actually in the conductive polymer
而且那個其實是在導電高分子中
It's what everyone was doing in the first place.
算是最一開始大家在做的事情
In the early days, everyone came to make biological detectors.
很前面的時候大家就來做生物偵測器這件事情
Because biometric sensors are very important
因為生物偵測器非常的重要
We're relatively not doing biometric detection ourselves right now.
我們自己現在比較沒有在做生物偵測
But many of the things we're doing
但是我們在做的很多一塊事
We are catching, in addition to organic electro-shock materials, we also have a large branch to capture the so-called circulating cancer cells
我們在抓,我們除了有機電擊材,我們還有一塊很大支在做那個所謂的循環癌細胞的捕捉
But we start with another big piece, about 40% to 50% of the research is in that direction
但是我們先是另外一大塊大概有40%到50%的研究在那個方向
So these two pieces are actually very big. I just mentioned a little bit about our first three pieces: Bioimaging, Biodetection, and Bioelectronic
所以這兩塊其實都很大,我剛剛有稍微提了一下我們先是這三塊就是Bioimaging,Biodetection,Bioelectronic
This part is about biological detection, including how we understand the mutation of cancer cells. We are doing this part.
這一塊的話生物偵測,包括我們去了解癌細胞的變異啊怎麼樣,這一塊我們都有在做
if
如果
We are at the action, we can see that you can do accenture, actuator, how is the actuator doing now?
我們在行動處,我們可以看到,你可以做accenture,actuator,那現在actuator這方面做得怎麼樣
The actuator is actually no, not now, and it is not doing it now, because the actuator is not doing it because of the lack of human resources.
actuator其實不,這下沒有,現在沒有在做,因為actuator因為人力資源不足,所以actuator現在沒有在做
actuator is
actuator是
It's not us, in fact, we are the other way around.
倒也不是我們其實反而我們是反過來
I think we are doing the more difficult
我覺得我們是在做比較難的
because we feel that saying
因為我們覺得說就是
Since there are such resources
既然有這樣的資源
It seems like we should be doing some comparisons
我們好像應該在做一些比較
to challenge something more difficult
去挑戰一些比較難的東西
I don't think we're doing simple
我倒不覺得我們在做簡單
Instead feel
反而覺得
Sometimes our lab sometimes complains to me that we are doing difficult things
有些時候我們的實驗室有時候要跟我抱怨說我們都在做難的
last question
最後一個問題
Hello, I am
你好我是
this speech is very good
這演講非常精彩
Just now I
我剛剛
The informant mentioned that
那位情報有提到就是說
Part of X-rayter
X-rayter的部分
I'm curious to say
我好奇的是說
when this vibration
這種振動的時候
it is this
它是這種
Its tension is similar to this part of their way to achieve the limit of human beings
它這種張力跟這部分他們辦法做到跟人類的極限為類似
The way they say if it's doing the same as the limit
他們辦法說如果它是做到跟極限為一樣的話
they are likely to do
他們有可能做
Increase
增加
That is to say, in the experiment, let some people
就是說在實驗上面比如讓有一些人他的
Insufficient grip strength
握力不足
or his
或者是他的
If they can't stand up, they can do it
比較站不起來的話他們辦法做
Enhance the human body ability to this part
把人體能力增強這個部分
It's just like being curious that he can follow
就是像蠻好奇就是他能夠跟
Bio-chamber mixed
生物室混合的
Uh uh this is not exclusion
呃 呃 這是沒有排斥喔
OK
OK
Yes, let's go
對啊 走走
I should prepare a hundred slimes today
我今天應該準備一百張史萊
Because I have Sly
因為這些我都有史萊
But I'm now Sly in the computer
但是我現在史萊其實在電腦裡啦
It might take a lot of time if I'm driving
我在開的話可能要花很多時間
I'll simply answer your question
我簡單的回答你這個問題好了
so we say
所以說我們
it actually
它其實
This x-ray is right
這個x-ray的 對
The so-called x-ray thing, I actually did some when I was in my doctoral class
所謂x-ray的東西其實我在我博士班的時候有做一些
Then some of my former collaborators and I
然後我跟我以前的一些的合作對象
included in australia
包含在澳洲
This piece of x-ray is doing very well in Australia
這x-ray這一塊在澳洲做得非常好
that's not you
那其實不是你
It's what we live for.
就是我們生涯臥力的東西啊
or how to actually x-ray
或怎樣其實x-ray的其實
The performance of conduction to molecules is very good
導電到份子的performance非常的好
very good
非常的好
just say
只是說
Just like what my classmate mentioned just now is
就好像我剛剛我同學提的就是
Where is your market and how do you find mass production
你的market在哪裡你怎麼找到mass production
That is the problem of commercial ratio
那個是commercial ratio的問題
that's a problem
那個有問題
But on Santipi I think they did a very, very good job
可是Santipi上我覺得他們做得非常非常的好
They learn some, of course they learn some very strange surrounds like what
他們學一些啊,當然他們學一些很奇怪的包圍像什麼
They say, you want to see what's the use of putting it like this
他們比如說,你想看這樣擺有什麼用
They can make a fish, so that the fish can move by itself
他們可以做一條魚,是要魚可以自己動
Or, in fact, when I was in BHD, I also received
或者說,其實我在BHD的時候,我也有接
We actually have pick up some of this like
我們實際上是有接一些這個像
Robot's Project
機械人的計畫
In fact, for robots, Actualator is very useful for robots
其實機械人,Actualator在機械人上是非常有用的
Because if you think about it, robots now use mechanical methods to do things
因為你想想看,現在機械人都是用機械的方式去做
The mechanical way is from metal material, so the weight is very heavy
機械的方式是來自金屬材,所以重量非常的重
What they want is that if I change the mechanical way into the material way
他們希望的是,如果我把機械的方式變成用材料的方式
In the way of Actualator, it's like you put ligaments on your robotic arm
像Actualator的方式的話,就好像你幫你的機械手臂裝上韌帶
He hopes that the Actualator is like a ligament, a soft substance
他希望這個Actualator是像韌帶一樣,是軟物質
It means that his idea comes from saying that the arm of a robot must have soft matter
等於他idea是來自於說機械人的手臂必須要有軟物質
Instead of using mechanical means to move the joints
而不再用機械的方式去進行關節的運動
Instead, the articulation is done in a material way
而是用材料的方式進行關節運動
They hope to achieve lightweight
他們希望藉此達到輕量化
Of course, this stock has been doing it back then
那當然,這股當年都有在做
But because I really didn't do it now
但是因為後來真的現在沒有在做
So I'm not quite sure where the newest has made it now
所以我不太確定現在最新的已經做到哪裡了
Early in about my time
早期的在大概我那時候的
In the early 2000s
2000年初期的時候
I think it is a very popular feel
我覺得是非常非常popular的一個feel
at the end make a
在最後做一個
There is one here
這邊有個
It's a question I really want to ask, isn't it?
非常想要問的問題是吧
right
對
microphone
麥克風
Excuse me
不好意思
hello i am a general public
您好我是一般民眾
I would like to ask some doctors for their views on the so-called 2045 plan
我想請教有博士對於所謂2045計畫的一種看法
news on the internet
就是在網路上的新聞
I don't know if it's true or it will come true
不曉得是真的還是會實現
It's like the idea in the Avatar movie.
就是類似阿凡達電影裡頭那種想法
First from the human will to control the machine and then
先從人類的意志控制機器然後
Make life more possible
讓生命的可能性更多
it's ok i want this stuff
沒有關係,我想這個東西
i never
我從來不
do not do any negation
不去做任何的否定
Neither do I, but I can't make any affirmations with you
我也不太,我也可是我沒辦法跟你做任何的肯定
Sorry, this is so far
不好意思,這在目前為止
We focus on the academics of Science
我們專注在Science的學術上
Um
嗯
don't be like i said
不要像我說的
Well, the Science I told you at the beginning is
嗯,一開始跟你們講的Science就是
Hollywood is great
好萊塢非常的厲害
they can
他們可以
tell us many ways
告訴我們很多的方式
but our own words
但是我們自己的話
we will feel academic
我們會覺得學術的
come to see for ourselves
走向我們自己來看
We used to think Alphabuy was impossible
我們以前也覺得阿法購不可能
but now you can
但是現在也可以
I never said no
I never said no
but I cannot say yes right now
but I cannot say yes right now
Someone thought about it before
阿法購以前有人想過
It's just that computers aren't fast enough
只是現在以前的電腦不夠快
The computer is not fast enough now
現在電腦不夠快
The computer is fast enough now
現在電腦夠快了
that is
就是
just right
才要對了
so i think
所以我想
Such a wonderful speech today
今天這麼精采的演講
I make a quick summary
我做一個很快的總結
Because Academia Sinica
因為中研院
What we do is basic research
我們做的是基礎的研究
just like this time
就是像這次
Boss mentioned this to us
有波士跟我們提的這個
Conductive
導電的
After the new material of organic polymer comes out
有機高分子這個新的材料出來了以後
Then we can find that it can be compared with biological cells
那我們可以發現說它可以跟生物細胞
Many things in living organisms can be done very effectively
生物體內的很多東西可以做非常有效
then unbroken binding
然後不破壞的結合
So we can use the outside world to conduct electricity
所以我們可以用外界用導電的方式
with current
用電流
Then go talk to creatures and change some creatures inside
然後去跟生物改變一些生物體內
or one of some of its functions
或者一個一些它的功能
Go can do some conversion or do some sides
去可以做一些轉換或做一些兩側
After all, there are still many, many, many possibilities for the application behind this.
那到底這個把後面的應用還是很多很多有很多的可能性
So its whole breaking point is in that one
所以它整個的突破點是在那一個
conductive polymer
導電高分子
that
那個
It is the whole discovery of conducting polymer
就是conducting polymer的那個整個的發現
This is a
這是一個
a jumping one
一個跳躍的一個
A Progressive Advancement in Academics
一個進步在學術界的進步
So under this basic research
所以在這種基礎研究下
For this thing in the future
對於這個東西到底將來
where will it go
會走到哪一個地步
We all don't know the truth now
我們現在都並不是完全真實的知道
so today again
所以今天又
That Dr. You gave us some direction
那個尤博士告訴了我們一些方向
Those directions are the ones that are going on now.
那這些方向都是現在正在進行的方向
So just had some very practical questions
所以剛剛有一些很實際的問題
Is it possible to do this
到底可不可以做這個
Can you do that back to the end?
可不可以做那個後面到底
What are the details of the impact it will have afterwards?
它之後會造成的影響細節是什麼
I think this is what we have to do in scientific research now
我想這都是我們現在科學研究要做的事情
because everyone knows
因為大家都知道
We now your laser is better than this thing
我們現在你的雷射比這個東西
lasers are everywhere
雷射到處都是
When the laser came out
當初雷射出來的時候
It's just that there are two conversions that can be connected inside.
只是說兩個能接裡頭的轉換
So when I found that
所以當初發現那個東西
It never occurred to me that lasers can now be used as scalpels
並沒有想到說現在雷射可以做手術刀
can do your music can save
可以做你的音樂都可以存
it's all behind
這都是後面的事情
So what we are doing in the hospital of traditional Chinese medicine is a kind of
所以在中醫院現在我們做的是一種
Very upstream basic research
非常比較上游的基礎研究
We hope to be able to find some direction
我們希望能夠找到一些方向
Pad some ground
墊地一些基礎
Find the one that can confirm which of these works
找到能夠確認這些是不是哪一個可行
what other possible directions
還有哪些可能的方向
Then there are many, many steps below
然後再來下面還有很多很多的步驟
this thing
這個東西
Is it possible to mass produce
是不是能夠量產
Is it possible to go down
是不是能夠往下做
Of course, the people behind will come to relay.
這是當然要後面的人再來接力
So we are doing a lot of trying
所以我們現在在做很多的嘗試
something will fail
有些東西會失敗
something will work out
有些東西會成功
I don't know this
這個都不知道
So now it's the work of doing these explorations
所以現在是在做這些探索的工作
Hope some people do upstream
希望要有一些人做上游
Some do midstream
有的做中游
Some say downstream
有的說下游
string this thing up
把這個東西可以串起來
so today
所以今天
So some things may be more abstract
所以有些東西也許比較抽象
It's because of what we're doing now
這是因為我們現在做的東西
yeah just look
是就是說看看
Are these things really useful?
是不是這些東西是真的有用
always try something first
總要先做一些嘗試
that tells the report
那告訴報告
Today's report is to tell you some
今天的報告是跟大家講一些
progress in this area
這方面的進展
that is maybe in a few years
那是也許再過幾年
we can stop
我們可以停
It's not about coming back and looking again
也不是回來再看看說
is there something in five years
五年以後是不是有什麼
some new developments
有些新的發展
or you can download from
或大家可以從
some media reports
一些媒體的報導
if there are some new developments
如果有一些新的發展的話
will also know
也會知道
So today our knowledge
所以今天我們的知識
want to
想要
This purpose is to tell you about some of the latest developments
這個目的就是告訴大家現在的一些最新的發展
So that's the purpose of all today
所以也是今天所有的一個目的
So before I wrap up I want to report back
所以在結束之前我想再報告一下
Preview next month in May
預告一下下個月五月份
Knowledge Trial on May 23rd
五月二十三號的知識想驗
We have another theme that is
我們有另外一個題材是
Genome Center
我們本院的基因體中心
Hong Shangcheng of Genome Research Center
基因體研究中心的洪尚成
Specific Researcher and Director
特定研究員兼主任
Tell us about molecular blood
要跟我們講分子折血
That fold is not a fold but a fold
那個折不是折是折疊的
So it's another field
所以它也是另外一個領域
have another development
有另外的發展
is actually a molecule
其實也是分子
but it's totally different
可是是完全不同的
From another point of view
從另外一個角度來看
I think today's time is also very tight
我想今天時間也很緊湊
Then let's thank you at this time
那趁這個時候我們再謝謝
Brilliant copy given to us by Dr. Xia Hua
由夏華博士給我們精采的一份
thank you for the glory
謝謝你能榮耀
Thanks
謝謝
Cai GuoICE
蔡國ICE